<?xml version='1.0'?>
<game name="stendhal" shortdescription="A multiplayer online adventures game">
  <updated date="2010/07/28"/>
  <version id="0.86.1"/>
  <status value="stable"/>
  <type value="game"/>
  <cssdoc url="css/stendhal.css"/>
  <rated>
    <entry>
      <![CDATA[
      <a href="http://happypenguin.org/show?stendhal"><img src="http://happypenguin.org/rateomatic?stendhal"></a>]]>    
    </entry>
    <entry>
      <![CDATA[<a href="http://freshmeat.net/projects/stendhal/"><img src="/images/fm_logo.png"></a>]]>    
    </entry>
<!-- broken link    <entry>
      <![CDATA[<a href="http://www.gamesites200.com/mpog/vote.php?id=1850"><img src="http://www.gamesites200.com/mpog/vote.gif" ALT="Paid and Free
MMORPG & MPOG" border="0"></a>]]>    
    </entry>-->
  <entry>
      <![CDATA[&nbsp;&nbsp; <script type="text/javascript" src="http://www.ohloh.net/projects/3711/widgets/project_users"></script>]]>
    </entry>

  </rated>
  <description><![CDATA[ 
Are you looking for adventure? Want to fight for riches?<br>
Develop yourself and your social standing? Meet new people?<br>
Do you want to be part of a brave new world?
<p/>
<a href="http://stendhalgame.org">Stendhal</a> is a fully fledged <b>multiplayer</b> online adventures game (MMORPG) developed using the Arianne game development system.
<p/>
Stendhal features a new, rich and expanding world in which you can explore towns, buildings, plains, caves and dungeons. <br>
You will meet NPCs and acquire tasks and quests for valuable experience and cold hard cash.<br>
Your character will develop and grow and with each new level up become stronger and better. With the money you acquire you can buy new items and improve your armour and weapons.<br>
And for the blood thirsty of you; satisfy your killing desires by roaming the world in search of evil monsters!
<p/>
Stendhal is totally platform independent, written using Java 1.5 and the Java2D environment.
<p/>
So what are you waiting for?! A whole new world awaits...]]>
  </description>
  <extended><![CDATA[
  <p/><h2>Want to help us?</h2>
  The game is right now <b>PLAYABLE</b> and <b>FUN</b>.<p/>
  We would really love to get your help <a href="http://stendhalgame.org/wiki/Navigation_for_Stendhal_Contributors">contributing</a> and if you are interested you can learn a lot more about Stendhal at <a href="http://stendhalgame.org/wiki/Stendhal">Stendhal's wiki</a>.

  <p/><h2>Play now!</h2>
  Stendhal uses Java Webstart technology that enables you to use always the latest version available without having to worry about updates.<br>
  Just click on the button to play.
  <p/><a href="http://arianne.sourceforge.net/jws/stendhal.jnlp"><img src="/images/webstart.png" alt="Click here to play"></a>
  ]]>
  </extended>
  <manual url="http://stendhalgame.org/wiki/StendhalManual"/>  
  <changelog><![CDATA[
<p><b>0.86.1</b>
<br><b>*bugfixes*</b>
<br>- If floating windows were saved under settings panel, move them on login
<br>- updater package does not use DefaultGameProperties, only use properties file, to make it easier for other projects to understand how to use updater without breaking it
<br>- use new 0.86.1 base for updater due to problems with webstart clients from 0.85
<br>- remove db_id entries from buddy list
<br>- offer deletion of update files in case of a security exception

<p><b>0.86</b>
<br><b>*world*</b>
<br>-new quest at the wizards tower in semos mountain
<br>-new music by semos dungeon, in semos and ados townhall, semos temple, ados church and in the forest
<br>-new sounds on the athor ship, in the ados sewers, at the ados city haven and some minor additions
<br>-Ados and Fado churches ring their bells at full and half hours
<br>-initial Hayunn dialog/tutorial streamlined and improved
<br>-Diogenes tells you about postman, he recently remembered that used to be his job
<br>-a sign at the flowers field which shows the meaning of these flowers
<br>-marked path from semos to ados city and to the athor ferry pier on ados coast
<br>-new npc added to ados market, who buys blue shield 
<br>-Simon in Ados church offers helpful guidance
<br>-blackjack max stake raised to 400
<br>-bakers want more button mushrooms

<br><b>*client*</b>
<br>-attack targets drawn as circles
<br>-settings panel uses icons and is always visible
<br>-new help menus for settings panel
<br>-"Remove account" button moved next to the account list
<br>-right click and ignore a player, or right click and unignore an already ignored player
<br>-/storemessage <player> <message> for using postman
<br>-karma scale bar (activated by asking Sarzina)

<br><b>*bugfixes*</b>
<br>-walkblocker tables have proper resistance
<br>-Mac OSX cmd key mapping
<br>-getting an amulet when killing thing

<br><b>*code*</b>
<br>-portals can do actions 
<br>-Messages from NPCs to offline players for postman can be stored in a table (without postman online)
<br>-SBoxLayout supports alignment and padding
<br>-support messages will get sent using postman if the player was offline
<br>-postman uses an admin action to store messages in table

<p><b>0.85</b>
<br><b>*features*</b>
<br>- all gui components use a new wood panel theme (even ones which did not have wood before)
<br>- character selection dialog after account login
<br>- login profiles can be cleaned up
<br>- right click and 'Where' yourself
<br>- /listproducers command for working NPCs
<br>- quest to help Phalk with food and clothes
<br>- slow down when walking over resisting entities
<br>- take resistance into consideration when choosing path
<br>- use more karma at the well and count activities
<br>- added descriptions to some npcs
<br>- new npc in ados church
<br>- new tutorial messages for receiving items and private messages
<br>- rats in semos village are not cowards

<br><b>*code*</b>
<br>- players can't use npc names or creature names
<br>- cannot add buddy who doesn't exist
<br>- refactored Kanmararn Soldiers quest
<br>- style code completely rewritten as a swing look & feel, and extended to all components used by stendhal
<br>- a script for calculating item drop rarities
<br>- quests history refactored to not use xml
<br>- many semos npcs reverted to not use xml for configuration
  
<br><b>*bugfixes*</b>
<br>- upper part of grain is not counted as grain (can move between grain fields)
<br>- raid creatures no longer have attack weakest profile even if the creature normally would
<br>- weekly item quest xp reward
<br>- quest completed check where completed state is set to other than 'done'
<br>- initial Hayunn dialog/tutorial cleaned up

<p><b>0.84</b>
<br><b>*features*</b>
<br>- new quest from Balduin if you have completed all other quests to get or collect rare weapons
<br>- daily and weekly item quests can ask for more than one of each item at once
<br>- eating, poisoned, grumpy and away status are shown in the stats panel
<br>- Dr. Feelgood can heal pets
<br>- Zoo Food quest is repeatable and food item request is randomised
<br>- pizza delivery missions selected by level
<br>- client can be started with username and password as parameters to bypass login gui (not for use on multi-user systems)
<br>- an arrow effect drawn for distance attacks
<br>- mrotho and diehelm brui sell arrows (and merenwen pays a bit less for arrows)
<br>- sarzina sells mega potions
<br>- temporary bans can be made using /ban
<br>- reason for ban is visible to player
<br>- new missile, a fire shuriken

<br><b>*code*</b>
<br>- new simple layout manager to replace the abandoned pagelayout
<br>- reworked zone configurators for Kill Dark Elves quest and for Kill Spiders quest.
<br>- reworked Daily Monster quest NPC engine
<br>- reworked kill quests to not clear player's information about previous killed creatures:
<br>  - Daily Monster quest
<br>  - Kill Gnomes quest
<br>  - Kill Dhohr Nuggetcutter quest
<br>  - Clean Storage Space quest
<br>  - Club Of Thorns quest
<br>  - Meet Hayunn quest
<br>  - Sad Scientist quest
<br>- npc conditions and actions for randomised item collection quests
<br>- fixed bug with xp display after death
<br>- ranged attack bug fixes on using up last missile and throwing from 1 tile away
<br>- email address field may be left completely empty on account creation 
<br>- /inspect command output improved for viewing quests, karma, and coordinates

<br><b>*website*</b>
<br>- performance optimisation
<br>- bugfixes including player display on firefox
<br>- spouse of a married player is displayed 

<p><b>0.83</b>
<br><b>*features*</b>
<br>- Rat City extended
<br>- Find the Rat Children quest
<br>- some creatures have attack strategy choosing weakest opponent (e.g. dragons, military commanders, bosses)
<br>- Zynn Iwuhos has some maps on display in the library
<br>- Tab completion for online nick names works now without /who called before
<br>- orc spearman creature
<br>- /atlas /faq and /manual commands to open useful pages in browser
<br>- Harold tweets trades, the official stendhal server uses <a href="http://twitter.com/stendhaltrade">http://twitter.com/stendhaltrade</a>
<br>- magical damage types of weapons (fire, ice ...)
<br>- resistance/vulnerability of creatures to magical weapons (fire, ice, ...)
<br>- attack sweeps look different depending on the attack type
<br>- Haizen's maze has music near the exit
<br>- Plan a new route when a player following a path hits another entity
<br>- single click for most actions and contextual mouse cursors (use /clickmode if you prefer doubleclick)
<br>- sub-zone teleport restrictions
<br>- NPCs can respond to emote actions
<br>- fertile ground inside houses
<br>- zone changing using mouse is possible
<br>- a family of NPCs holidaying in Ados
<br>- more rats and zones for the Pied Piper quest

<br><b>*bugfixes*</b>
<br>- archer behaviour
<br>- zero value offers supported at market
<br>- Monogenes easier to use
<br>- kill spiders and dark elves quests check you killed creatures from those relevant areas
<br>- recover automatically from corrupted cache files
<br>- ghosts have low hp like intended
<br>- turns walking along a path are now smooth
<br>- using a portal from distance walks the player to the portal
<br>- the client can cope better with differing tile sizes

<br><b>*code*</b>
<br>- creatures xml split into smaller parts
<br>- attacks are now events
<br>- signs can show an image instead of 'You read: ' text, or a description
<br>- Charas Converter jar available to download

<br><b>*website*</b>
<br>- new domain stendhalgame.org
<br>- rss feeds


<p><b>Stendhal 0.82.1</b>
<br>- new command /clickmode to toggle between single click walking and double click walking
<br>- fixed movement to drop target (only Microsoft Windows was affected)
<br>- fixed /mute not being stored across restarts
<br>- fixed pets not ownable

<p><b>Stendhal 0.82</b>
<br><b>*features*</b>
<br>- single click movement
<br>- Easter Bunny
<br>- Pied Piper quest
<br>- open manual on key F1
<br>- added /volume support for sound
<br>- asynchronous database access
<br>- Kalavan orb
<br>- Sad Scientist quest
<br>- Dice Gambling prizes upgraded

<br><b>*admin*</b>
<br>- new /script AdminPortal.class
<br>- support answer contains the name of the asking player in the greeting

<br><b>*website*</b>
<br>- added detail view of news items on their own pages (with nice urls)
<br>- improvements to various icons
<br>- reorganisation and cleanup of http://arianne.sf.net

<br><b>*bug fixes*</b>
<br>- Carmen only asks for her quest if the player is at least level 2.
<br>- improved stability of the client in uncommon situations
<br>- stat changes that occurred during zone change (like losing xp on death) did not update the stats window.
<br>- click walking is now a lot smoother
<br>- fixed Harold telling players about expiring earnings every minute

<p><b>Stendhal 0.81.2</b>
<br><b>*bug fixes*</b>
<br>- fixed a crash on Linux using alsa (non pulse) audio drivers and Sun Java (not OpenJDK) 
  if all channels are in use by another application
<br>- fixed rare InvalidVersionExceptions in the network code on high latency connections 
  (for example for people living outside Europe to an server in Europe)
<br>- handle failure to load sprite images more gracefully
<br>- improved logging of uncaught exceptions 
<p>
0.81.2 contains the first results of the Client Quality Weeks. Thanks everyone for providing
your error log files and please continue to do so.

<p><b>Stendhal 0.81.1</b>
<br><b>*bug fixes*</b>
<br>- fixed an issue with 0 hp created by logging out while dying (thanks to Andrzej Kofanski)
<br>- prevent client crash on empty soundNameList
<br>- renamed admins.list to admins.txt to simplify installation on windows with hidden file name extensions
<br>- fixed a server side classpath issue
<br>- updated to Marauroa 3.5 to fix an issue with null-values in the timedate columns in gameEvents and account

<p><b>Stendhal 0.81</b>
<br><b>*features*</b>
<br>- player stats moved from the character window to the side panel
<br>- a dragbar for making the game screen smaller (handy for netbooks)
<br>- new quest from Ouchit with new NPC in ados forest
<br>- having multiple correct answers for a riddle now possible
<br>- athor labyrinth redrawn 
<br>- h2 database support
<br>- ignored players are drawn as black forms

<br><b>*bug fixes*</b>
<br>- numerous small map fixes
<br>- poorly organised tilesets reorganised
<br>- list quests output fixed
<br>- split grain field
<br>- show a long dash rather than a negative number for required xp for max level players
<br>- feedback on using portals and chests from too far away
<br>- fixed "Drag and drop sometimes misses slots and hits ground instead" (was for drag and drop onto same slot)
<br>- better reject message for inactive accounts
<br>- fixed leander stealing all the pizzas of a player who has failed the quest previously

<br><b>*code*</b>
<br>- sound system rewritten and using oggs 
<br>- more client refactoring

<br><b>*website*</b>
<br>- fixed a directory traversing vulnerability on http://arianne.sf.net
  (special thanks to Ed Milner for discovering and reporting it)
<br>- account history
<br>- adminlevel shown

<p><b>See <a href="http://arianne.cvs.sourceforge.net/viewvc/*checkout*/arianne/stendhal/doc/CHANGES.txt">all past changes</a></b>]]>
  </changelog>
  <screenshots>
    <image name="raid65.png"/>
    <image name="20070522_stendhal.jpg"/>
    <image name="20070522_1_stendhal.jpg"/>
    <image name="20070522_2_stendhal.jpg"/>
    <image name="20070522_stendhal.jpg"/>
    <image name="20070414_stendhal.jpg"/>
    <image name="20070130_stendhal.jpg"/>
    <image name="20060903_stendhal.jpg"/>
    <image name="20060324_stendhal.jpg"/>
    <image name="20060303_stendhal.jpg"/>
    <image name="20060310_stendhal.jpg"/>
    <image name="20060304_stendhal.jpg"/>
    <image name="20051220_stendhal.jpg"/>
    <image name="20051023_stendhal.jpg"/>
  </screenshots>
  <files>
    <file type="FULL binary with sounds" name="stendhal-FULL-XXX.zip">
      <description>This file contains the FULL stendhal client with sounds. Download this to play online.</description>
      <os>
        <entry name="win32" status="100"/>
        <entry name="linux" status="100"/>
        <entry name="macosx" status="100"/>
      </os>
    </file>
    <file type="binary" name="stendhal-XXX.zip">
      <description>This file contains the stendhal client. Download this to play online.</description>
      <os>
        <entry name="win32" status="100"/>
        <entry name="linux" status="100"/>
        <entry name="macosx" status="100"/>
      </os>
    </file>
    <file type="map editor binary" name="stendhal_mapeditor-2.00.zip">
      <description>This file contains the stendhal map editor. Download this to create new maps. Send them to us if you want them to appear on next releases. Use the tmx file format.</description>
      <os>
        <entry name="win32" status="100"/>
        <entry name="linux" status="100"/>
        <entry name="macosx" status="100"/>
      </os>
    </file>
    <file type="server script binary" name="stendhal-server-XXX.zip">
      <description>This file contains the stendhal server files. See http://stendhalgame.org/wiki/Host_a_Stendhal_Server</description>
      <os>
        <entry name="win32" status="100"/>
        <entry name="linux" status="100"/>
        <entry name="macosx" status="100"/>
      </os>
    </file>
    <file type="source" name="stendhal-XXX-src.tar.gz">
      <description>This file contains the source code to build stendhal. See http://stendhalgame.org/wiki/Stendhal#Build_information </description>
      <os>
        <entry name="win32" status="100"/>
        <entry name="linux" status="100"/>
        <entry name="macosx" status="100"/>
      </os>
    </file>
  </files>
  <servers>
    <server name="Game server" url="http://stendhalgame.org/"/>
  </servers>
  <authors>
    <entry name="kymara" url="http://www.ohloh.net/accounts/kymara"/>
    <entry name="Hendrik" url="http://www.ohloh.net/accounts/nhnb"/>
    <entry name="kiheru" url="http://www.ohloh.net/accounts/kiheru"/>
    <entry name="madmetzger" url="http://www.ohloh.net/accounts/madmetzger"/>
    <entry name="yoriy" url="http://www.ohloh.net/accounts/yoriy"/>
    <entry name="bluelads" url="https://www.ohloh.net/accounts/Bluelads99"/>
    <entry name="storyteller" url="http://www.ohloh.net/accounts/tigertoes"/>
    <entry name="laguz" url="https://www.ohloh.net/accounts/Laguz"/>
    <entry name="tigertoes" url="http://www.ohloh.net/accounts/tigertoes"/>
    <entry name="plassy" url="http://www.ohloh.net/projects/stendhal/contributors/"/>
    <entry name="durkham" url="http://www.ohloh.net/projects/stendhal/AstridSawatzky"/>
    <entry name="MartinF" url="http://www.ohloh.net/accounts/martinfuchs"/>
    <entry name="mort" url="http://www.ohloh.net/projects/stendhal/contributors/"/>
    <entry name="Miguel Angel Blanch Lardin" url="http://arianne.sourceforge.net/wiki/index.php/MiguelAngelBlanchLardin"/>
    <entry name="Chad3f" url="http://www.ohloh.net/projects/stendhal/contributors/"/>
    <entry name="Steve I." url="http://arianne.sourceforge.net/wiki/index.php/StephenIerodiaconou"/>
    <entry name="Kim Purnell Samoa" url=""/>
    <entry name="Danter" url="http://arianne.sourceforge.net/wiki/index.php/Danter"/>
    <entry name="Laurent Soubrevilla" url=""/>
    <entry name="Hans Haggstrom" url="http://www.iki.fi/zzorn/"/>
    <entry name="Jonas aka Damosh" url=""/>
    <entry name="TheGeneral" url=""/>

  </authors>
</game>
