<?xml version="1.0"?>
<page name="stendhal" shortdescription="A multiplayer online adventures game">
  <updated date="2016-09-13"/>
  <version id="1.21"/>
  <status value="stable"/>
  <type value="game"/>
  <playnow url="https://stendhalgame.org/account/mycharacters.html" image="images/playbutton.png"/>
  <keywords>Stendhal, game, online game, online games, multiplayer game, adventure game, multiplayer online games, MMORGP, RPG, role playing game, arianne</keywords>
  <short-description>Stendhal is a fun friendly and completely free multiplayer online adventure game with an old school feel.</short-description>
<!--
  <rated>
   
    <entry><![CDATA[
      <a href="http://happypenguin.org/show?stendhal"><img src="http://happypenguin.org/rateomatic?stendhal"></a>]]>    
    </entry>
    <entry>
      <![CDATA[<a href="http://freecode.com/projects/stendhal/"><img src="/images/fm_logo.png"></a>]]>    
    </entry>
    <entry>
      <![CDATA[<a href="http://www.gamesites200.com/mpog/vote.php?id=1850"><img src="http://www.gamesites200.com/mpog/vote.gif" ALT="Paid and Free
MMORPG & MPOG" border="0"></a>]]>    
    </entry>
  <entry>
      <![CDATA[&nbsp;&nbsp; <script type="text/javascript" src="http://www.ohloh.net/projects/3711/widgets/project_users"></script>]]>
    </entry>
  </rated>
  -->
  
  <description><![CDATA[ 
<p>Stendhal has a huge and rich world. You can explore cities, forest, mountains, mines, plains, caves and dungeons.</p>
<p>
You could meet over 250 NPCs, many will give you tasks and quests for valuable experience, shiny gold, but mainly a warm fuzzy feeling. You may be asked to help protect land or people from danger, feed the hungry, heal the sick, make someone happy, solve a puzzle, play a game or simply lend a hand. You can keep track of your progress using a Travel Log.</p>
<p>
Your character will develop and grow and with each new level up become stronger and better. With the money you acquire you can buy new items and improve your armour and weapons, trade with friends, or look for what other players are giving away in the 'community chest'.</p>
<p>
If you just want to fight that helps too - the cities could get overrun by monsters without you!</p>
<blockquote>
Start playing, get hooked... and if you like, get the source code, and add your own ideas!</blockquote>
<p>So what are you waiting for? A whole new world awaits...</p>
]]>
  </description>
  <extended><![CDATA[
  <h2>Start playing, get hooked...</h2>
  <p>With Java installed, playing is as simple as clicking Play Now on <a href="https://stendhalgame.org">stendhalgame.org</a>. You can play Stendhal on Windows, Mac and Linux, it is completely free and all open source.
</p>
<p>There is an ingame tutorial, a <a href="https://stendhalgame.org/wiki/Stendhal_Manual">manual</a> and a <a href="https://stendhalgame.org/wiki/Stendhal_Beginner%27s_Guide">beginners guide</a>.
<h2>Get the source code, and add your own ideas!</h2>
  <p>Stendhal is part of the Arianne project and framework for developing games. It's a great project to get involved in, if you are interested in learning to develop Java for example. If you don't want to code you can help with graphics, history, dialogue, quest ideas, music and more. Join a team of developers from all over the world who create the game just for fun, and of course for free, in our spare time. We would really love to get your help <a href="https://stendhalgame.org/development.html">contributing</a>.</p>
  ]]>
  </extended>
  <manual url="https://stendhalgame.org/wiki/Stendhal_Manual/Controls_and_Game_Settings"/>  
  <changelog><![CDATA[
<h3 id="v1.21">Stendhal 1.21: Get the party ready</h3>

<b>world</b><ul>
<li> Pets can drink 'medicine' even when they aren't hungry. Making them easier to maintain in battle.
<li> New trader NPC (Mizuno) travels around remote parts of Ados selling ice arrows for black pearls.
<li> Rebalancing vampire, chaos swords.
<li> Photo booth at Mine Town Revival festival
<li> Small improvements to maps
<li> Small improvements to item and monster descriptions
</ul>

<b>client</b><ul>
<li> Default action of chest changed to open/inspect instead of look
</ul>

<b>fixes</b><ul>
<li> Help For the Harvest quest works again.
</ul>

<b>code</b><ul>
<li> In TeleporterBehaviour, zoneName.startsWith() now checks a variable so teleporting NPCs can be a little more customizable.
<li> TeleporterBehaviour can now be passed an array of zones to choose from or leave null for the default list.
</ul>



<h3 id="v1.20">Stendhal 1.20: Trust and Confidence</h2>
<b>world</b><ul>
<li> Humans lose conscious when scuba gear is take off under water
<li> Improved thunderstorms
<li> Archer combat is now visible
<li> Harold understands "prolong all" now
</ul>

<b>code</b><ul>
<li> Support Postgres databases in addition to H2 (recommended) and MySQL
<li> Setup Travis for continuous integration tests and fixed some order dependent tests 
<li> Migrated test coverage analysis from Cobertura to Jacoco 
<li> Git repository is mirrored instantaneously between Github and Sourceforge in both directions
<li> Yearly special event quests now pick up the current year as part of their quest slot automatically
<li> Backend for puzzles
</ul>

<b>fixes</b><ul>
<li> Christmas quest "Goodies for Rudolph" is now repeatable next year
<li> Fixed maximization state being sometimes saved incorrectly.
<li> Database index are now created automatically
</ul>

  
  
<h3 id="v1.19">Stendhal 1.19: Deep Sea</h2>
<b>world</b><ul>
<li> new interesting under water zone
<li> new quest for a scuba diving license
<li> new Kraken creature
<li> Zekiel can make enhanced lion shields
<li> cats can drink milk now
<li> map improvements
</ul>

<b>code</b><ul>
<li> fixed compiler warnings and code cleanup
</ul>

<b>client</b><ul>
<li> added cancel buttons on all dialog boxes (for window managers which do not add an X to the title bar)
</ul>



<h3 id="v1.18">Stendhal 1.18: Voyages</h2>
<b>world</b><ul>
<li> a half elf girl and an distillery customer share their stories at Ados market
<li> Improving dialogue of Lil Johnnny
<li> Saskia sells umbrellas
</ul> 

<b>website</b><ul>
<li> zone names labels on world map
<li> http://arianne.sourceforge.net is moving to https://arianne-project.org
</ul> 

<b>fixes</b><ul>
<li> fixed status resistance items being forgetting their status value
<li> fixed turning left and right of character on character creation web page
<li> fixed map in Orril Dungeon -3
<li> fixed kill enemy quests getting stuck
</ul> 

<b>code</b><ul>
<li> Webstart starter will be able to check both arianne-project.org and arianne.sourceforge.net for additional files.
  So if SourceForge goes down again for a week, webstart will still be able to download Stendhal
<li> code quality improvements
</ul> 
  
<h3 id="v1.17">Stendhal 1.17: Water from above and below</h3>
<b>world</b><ul>
<li> Varying weather at outside zones
<li> A new fish swimming along the coast in Ados City
<li> Clubs and swords are visible during fights
<li> Added to Daily Item Quest list: 5 olives, 2 marbles
<li> Drunken player speech is now more confusing and depends on the state of drunkenness
<li> Different "elf" head for players and NPCs
<li> New corpse for bone dragon
<li> New item medicinal ring: Slightly protects against poisoning
<li> Mainio boots reward instead of steel boots from Kanmararn Soldiers quest
<li> Corpse descriptions state the creature name, instead of just the creature class
<li> Animated flame tiles replaced in int_semos_wizards_tower_1
</ul> 

<b>chat</b><ul>
<li> More visible new chat message indication
<li> Links to stendhalgame.org in the chat log can be opened with a mouse click
<li> Add hotkeys for cycling through chat log tabs: "Ctrl+Shift+left/right"
<li> Alias "/status" for command "/sentence"
<li> Alias "zucchini" for "courgette", Alias "armour" for "armor", Alias "color" for "colour", Alias "extend" for "prolong"
<li> "sentence" is now displayed in player description when using "Look"
</ul>

<b>client</b><ul>
<li> Can restore window width, height, and maximized state
<li> Drawing weather can be disabled in settings
<li> Active entities reset animated sprite index to 1 to appear standing when stopped
<li> Zombie status is indicated by making the player green
</ul>

<b>fixes</b><ul>
<li> Fix player cannot move after zombie status wears off
<li> Karma reward for quests: Kill Dhohr Nuggetcutter, Coal for Haunchy
<li> Refactored plant/cactus_2.png, object/row_boat.png
<li> Reporting killers on an entity death no longer lists all attackers at the time of death
<li> The server no longer sends perceptions for deleted entities
</ul>

<b>code</b><ul>
<li> Organized outfit parts into subdirectories
<li> Changed "player_base" outfit type to "body"
<li> A new script for replacing maps on a running server
</ul>
  

<h3 id="v1.16">Stendhal 1.16: Lil' Snowflake</h3>

<b>world</b><ul>
<li> Semos city is decorated for Christmas 
<li> Falling snow 
<li> Leaderhosen outfit
</ul>
<b>code</b><ul>
<li> weather layer
</ul>


<h3 id="v1.15.1">Stendhal 1.15.1: Poisoned Death</h3>
<ul><li><b>Security fix:</b> Summon scroll creatures poisoning a moster resulted in multiple corpse
</ul>

<h3 id="v1.15">Stendhal 1.15</h3>

<b>world</b><ul>
<li> Mine Town Revival Weeks are celebrated again!
<li> new quest: Finn Farmer has an important message
<li> better fitting curves to limit player stats
</ul>
<b>client</b><ul>
<li> repeatable quests are marked in progress log
<li> added support for translucency sprites on systems which are fast enough
</ul>
<b>website</b><ul>
<li> updated world map
</ul>
<b>admins</b><ul>
<li> admins can summon public chests
<li> admins can remove sentences
</ul>
<b>code</b><ul>
<li> small bug fixes
<li> code cleanup, fixed compiler warnings
</ul>


<h3 id="v1.14">Stendhal 1.14</h3>
<b>world</b><ul>
<li> new park in Fado city, south of church
<li> Easter map for Fado city
</ul>

<b>website</b><ul>
<li> unified search: creatures, items, quests, achievements, players, world guide, player's guide
<li> integration of wiki pages
<li> detail pages for quests, regions and dungeons
<li> links from NPC, items and creatures to related quests
<li> new, cleaner layout with drop down menus
<li> breadcrumbs for easier navigation
<li> gallery for screenshots
<li> website now works on small devices
</ul>

<b>fixes</b><ul>
<li> length of text messages limited and line breaks fixed on Java 7/8
<li> wedding ring supports double click
<li> message on shocked
<li> code cleanup and documentation improvements
<li> excessly high atk and def level are capped for fighters with little experience 
  (average players should not notice much of a difference)
</ul>



<h3 id="v1.13">Stendhal 1.13</h3>
<b>World</b><ul>
<li> Nice zone names
<li> Dragon slayer achievement
<li> Xeno helmet added to NPC purchasing shops
<li> Improvements to maps, most notable a makeover in hell
<li> Rats are so hungry that they are not scared by weak people anymore
</ul>


<b>Fixes</b><ul>
<li> Fixed webstart on Oracle Java (for Windows users)
<li> Postman messages are now filtered by the ignore list
<li> Fixed item description for canned tuna (item name underlining)
<li> Fixed a karma exploit on accepting accpeted quests (1.12.1)
<li> Fixed PVP defense against weaker players (1.12.1)
</ul>

<b>Website</b><ul>
<li> Removed myopenid as it is going to be discontinued
</ul>

<b>Developers</b><ul>
<li> If you developed a game based on stendhal and use the automatic updater, you will need to edit game.properties and add UPDATE_SIGNER_KEY. The required value will printed in the webstart console.
</ul>



<h3 id="v1.12">Stendhal 1.12</h3>
<b>World</b><ul>
<li> New Christmas maps for bank, townhall, storage (Eonnas house, all Semos)
<li> Meet Santa and Rudolph
<li> Dragon now notice small players right in front
<li> Reworked normal storage interior
<li> More creature descriptions
<li> Mew stocking items, deleting coal
<li> New sounds and images
</ul>

<b>Fixes</b><ul>
<li> Fixing tiles on several maps
<li> Sometimes xp reward for killing creatures was too low, if the player logged out during the fight
<li> On expire of a special outift, a message was displayed, even when the outfit has been removed beforehand
</ul>

<b>Website</b><ul>
<li> Display name of ip-address on login history
</ul>

<b>Developers</b><ul>
<li> Replaced commons-lang.jar with guava.jar (needs to be changed in Eclise: Project | Properties | Build Path | Libraries)
</ul>


<h3 id="v1.11">Stendhal 1.11</h3>
<b>World</b><ul>
<li> Mine Town Weeks are celebrated
<br>  -- New Paper chase quest
<br>  -- New Sokoban game
<br>  -- all the games from last years festival are back
<li> Margaret accepts coupons
<li> New look for Semos plains
<li> More creature descriptions
<li> Added fairy cakes to daily item quest
<li> Icons to indicate healer and merchant NPCs
<li> Pebbles sprite replaced by rocks in some collision areas on maps
<li> New achievement: Fisherman
</ul>

<b>Client</b><ul>
<li> Notifies player of last login attempt
<li> Subwindows on the right side panel can be arranged by the user
</ul>

<b>Fixes</b><ul>
<li> Screen flashing during zone colouring change has been fixed
<li> Resizing karma bar no longer causes it to flash
<li> Font setting changes opening travel log window has been fixed
</ul>

<b>Code</b><ul>
<li> Status icon positions are automatically arranged
<li> Poisoning and new status effects handled with new system
</ul>

<div class="unimportant">

<p><b>1.10</b>
<br><b>*world*</b>
<br>- More creature descriptions
<br>- Added 3rd frame to cyclops and cave troll for smoother walking effect
<br>- Animated sprite for diamond
<br>- Touched up sprites for some creatures
<br>- NPC Seremela has a new sprite
<br>- Touched up elf ears for some NPCs
<br>- Added reversible path on collision to Eheneumniranin
<br>- Added achievement "A Bit Xenophobic"
<br>- Reworked area around ghost in Ados city_n

<br><b>*client*</b>
<br>- Now handles images for multiple status effect icons/animations
<br>- On multi-screen systems updater windows open on the screen with the mouse pointer
<br>- Shop signs can have animated item images
<br>- Game opens in the initial window

<br><b>*fixes*</b>
<br>- Fixing table entities in Kalavan houses
<br>- Exchanging white round tables in fado city
<br>- Clicking the menu button when the menu is open, closes it

<br><b>*code*</b>
<br>- NPC sound effects are handled by server
<br>- Sheep sounds are generated server side
<br>- Domestic animals and NPCs use the same idea handling code in the client

<p><b>1.09</b>

<br><b>*world*</b>
<br>- New quest: Traps for Klaas
<br>- New quest: Help with the Harvest
<br>- New achievement: A Bit Xenophobic (inactive)
<br>- New item: xeno helmet dropped by xenocium
<br>- Captain of Athor Ferry named Captain Brownbeard now
<br>- Sprite fixes:
<br>-- Ogre soldier's front & back facing helmet fixed to match side view
<br>-- All dark elves now have elf ears, Elf ears on many elves made more visible and cleaned up
<br>-- Re-drew/touched up many creature sprites including Grobble monster and Winged blurble
<br>- Added new harmless corpses to the following creatures:
    ice giant, elder giant, lord durin, cave troll, imperial general giant, master giant,
    black giant, amazoness giant, kasarkutominubat
<br>- Sound effect played when player dies
<br>- Added to list of maps where Rose Leigh will not teleport
<br>- Most blue items moved from Daily Item Quest to Weekly
<br>- Added dwarvish legs to Femme Fatale's shop
<br>- Sound effects for fishing source and water spring source

<br><b>*client*</b>
<br>- Karma indicator bar flashes for karma change
<br>- Movement prediction when using keyboard adapts to network latency

<br><b>*fixes*</b>
<br>- Alice Farmer answers to "crepes suzette"
<br>- TeleporterBehaviour badZones table updated
<br>- Replaced tilesets:
    table_white_round tileset with table_white, bench_white, orb_table, skull_post
<br>- Marked apothecary's lab and cabin as inaccessible
<br>- Player's head no longer shows when walking in minecart tunnels in -2_semos_mine_n_e2
<br>- Item names in shop lists are now properly underlined
<br>- Spurious double click usages on items not meant to be usable removed

<br><b>*code*</b>
<br>- PassiveNPCs using random paths can be set to have a maximum movement radius
<br>- NPCs can be set to reverse their path on collision
<br>- QuestCheckingPortal can now check quest state

<p><b>1.08</b>
<br><b>*world*</b>
<br>- New NPC and quest in Nalwor Flower Shop: Restock Flower Shop
<br>- New achievements: Nalwor's Bane and Feeling Blue
<br>- New puppy NPC in Semos City
<br>- Rodent trap added to Daily Item Quest
<br>- Some new creature sound effects
<br>- Some new creature corpses
<br>- New NPC type: PassiveNPC
<br>- Warning messages for dangerous areas now show up in client display
<br>- Sound plays when player/creature blocks an attack
<br>- Item names have a new highlighting mode
<br>- Twin swords have a bit of DEF again
<br>- Teddies can be hugged
<br>- Food and drinks have "Eat" and "Drink" menu items, instead of "Use"
<br>- House keys are no longer dropped on death
<br>- Bufferflies added to Semos Plains North
<br>- Rabbits added to Fado City
<br>- Fish added to fountain in Ados City
<br>- 3 kitten added to Felina's house


<br><b>*client*</b>
<br>- Option to turn off creature speech bubbles
<br>- Fixed accidental looting on drag by deactivating ctrl-click as looting command
<br>- Immediate response when starting to move with arrow keys
<br>- Attack sprites are scaled according to attacker size
<br>- Player now faces attack target if not doing so on each turn


<br><b>*fixes*</b>
<br>- quest log of EmotionCrystals fixed
<br>- Removed background noise from many sound effects
<br>- Pressing an arrow key always tries to move one tile
<br>- Producers don't ask to come back in the past under certain conditions anymore
<br>- Hayunn won't give more than one task at a time
<br>- Stone style for client fixed

<br><b>*code*</b>
<br>- @Override added where applicable
<br>- Reduced visibility of several classes, methods and fields
<br>- Unused old code removed

<p><b>1.07</b>

<br><b>*world*</b>
<br>- New quest from Julius: Emotion Crystals
<br>- New items required by Mayor Chalmers and Hazel
<br>- New food requirements for Katinka's animals
<br>- Snake pit beneath Ados caves
<br>- New dropped items: elvish hat
<br>- New quest items: stone legs
<br>- More lights on Ados market, around Athor island and more light effects 
<br>- New look for mountain orc 
<br>- Dwarves rebuilt rails in Semos Mine
<br>- New creatures: Mimics, cobra, king cobra, and lamia 
<br>- More sounds and descriptions for creatures
<br>- Creatures added to the mountains
<br>- Pdiddi warns first customers about the risk of his pills
<br>- Pianos and clocks have sound effects
<br>- Toilets and sinks have running water sound effects
<br>- Athor's ferry has "creaking" sound effects
<br>- Jef feels better but still wants to hear from his mom
<br>- Pushable stone blocks 
<br>- Background music in hell 
<br>- Growing cherry trees on Orril Mountain

<br><b>*client*</b>
<br>- A lot of redrawn tilesets
<br>- style changeable from settings menu

<br><b>*fixes*</b>
<br>- Special character in offline messages (postman messages) work now
<br>- Fixed imperial defender sprite
<br>- Map fixes (e.g. collision errors and layers)
<br>- Slightly increasing drop rates for blue items

<p><b>1.06</b>
<br><b>*world*</b>
<br>- more light in Ados city
<br>- some creatures drop blue items now
<br>- more creature descriptions added
<br>- new sprite shown when blood and corpses setting is turned off
<br>- new sound effects for multiple creatures
<br>- Leander explains his task better 
<br>- new corpses for slimes, ents and stone golems
<br>- dwarvish legs now available
<br><b>*fixes*</b>
<br>- Alice Farmer understands players better
<br>- Vincento Price can count correctly
<br>- Collision touchups around trees on many maps
<br>- Elementals in hell can't collide any longer
<br>- "Far South" achievement reachable again

<p><b>1.05</b>
<br><b>*world*</b>
<br>- added Rudolph and a quest for goodies
<br>- added reindeer moss as a seasonal goody
<br>- Santa is out for Christmas

<br><b>*client*</b>
<br>- A lot of redrawn images
<br>- The game screen can be scaled. The scaling can be turned off in settings to get the old 
behaviour
<br>- Karma bar fits to the width of the left panel
<br>- Travel log updates to font preference change immediately
<br>- Font size used in the client can be changed

<br><b>*fixes*</b>
<br>- fixed tic-tac-toe board not being drawn when the top left corner is not on screen
<br>- fixed a bug that could cause items being lost in trade
<br>- fixed the automatic scrolling of the chat log sometimes turning off by itself
<br>- several small fixes to entity views sometimes missing changes


</div>
]]>
<!-- 
<![CDATA[


<p><b>1.04</b>

<br><b>*world*</b>
<br>- Mine Town Revival Weeks!
<br>- Semos and the Mine Town are decorated for the celebrations
<br>- new paper chase quest which leads players all over the world
<br>- Ketteh now gets help from the guards, if players without any clothes(!) ignore her warning
<br>- jail exit is straight to outside the cell

<br><b>*client*</b>
<br>- replaced the separate menu buttons with one large menu 
<br>- HP bar of ignored players is drawn in full color to make them visible at night
<br>- chat spam filter takes the length of the messages into account

<br><b>*fixes*</b>
<br>- webstart client now uses a styled font (e. g. for the quest log)
<br>- fixed players becoming invisible because of broken attack target reference
<br>- trading stack items properly
<br>- map fixes
<br><b>*website*</b>
<br>- added a little pumpkin
<p>
<b>1.03</b>
<br><b>*world*</b>
<br>- Ados Botanical Gardens
<br>- new lamps 
<br>- map layering and collisions fixes
<br>- new blend mode for enabling lighting in any zone
<br>- Monogenes informs players about public chest
<br>- 3 achievements activated 
<br><b>*fixes*</b>
<br>- don't accidently pick the first item on click spam on an item which was used up
<br>- fixed return from adventure island into the wall
<br>- Monogenes map is up to date now
<br>- Ados market signs more specific now
<br>- Adena got vegetables from farms near Semos
<br><b>*internal*</b>
<br>- creates selenium test for the stendhal website
<br>- actions use item paths where applicable
<br>- journal for merchants
<br><b>*website*</b>
<br>- email-address can now be changed


<p><b>1.02</b>
<br><b>*world*</b>
<br>- clocks around the world show the server time
<br>- vampires change their appearance depending on their attack status
<br>- boy guardian in Semos Road East warns new player who miss a shield
<br>- reduce Starkad's cost for lower level creatures and increase for higher level
<br>- ninjas use shurikens for ranged attack
<br>- more dragons breath fire
<br>- lamps and lights effects added to ados market, gnome village, catacombs, haunted house, amazon island and more
<br>- zone colouring added to hell, new dreamscape map, maze (randomised), adventure island, afterlife, drow tunnels, rat city
<br>- semos temple and tavern upstairs maps reworked
<br>- new npc food seller and signs for ados market

<br><b>*client*</b>
<br>- fancy tutorial speech bubbles
<br>- nicer look of the attack circles
<br>- slash commands have tab completion, suggestions of close matches for misstyped commands
<br>- a second splitter between the left panel and the game screen
<br>- added textual description to the karma bar tooltip
<br>- away and grumpy indicators show the reason in their tooltips
<br>- the client gets ranged attack information from the server instead of trying to guess which attacks are ranged
<br>- quit dialog gets keyboard focus so that it is possible to exit the game without a mouse
<br>- improved key handling and font sizes on Mac
<br>- refined money and cheese sprites

<br><b>*fixes*</b>
<br>- automatic walking behind a slow creature or npc will now properly try to find the way around it
<br>- lucky charms are bound to the player at loot time
<br>- fixed removal of choking, away and grumpy icons that failed to be removed under certain conditions
<br>- make killer bees less dangerous(!)
<br>- various NPC, quest and map fixes

<br><b>*code*</b>
<br>- added script for adding/removing/alter/list of NPC's transitions.
<br>- creatures can have different nature for ranged attacks than in melee
<br>- events can trigger animations
<br>- some dependency cleanup

<p>
<b>1.01</b>
<br><b>*world*</b>
<br>- Venethiel teaches players about Haizen's maze
<br>- Will warns players leaving Semos city 
<br>- reworked Fado hotel restaurant 
<br>- more creature descriptions added
<br>- moved Semos city wall into the city
<br>- Monogenes is now next to the bird station in Semos city
<br>- Users can grab items bound to them even if they are under another player
<br>- Player bound items do not move under pushed player, unless they belong to the said player
<br>- Mixed creature fighting profiles. Used mainly for dragons, who will attack at a distance if they can't get close to player
<br>- killer bees are a new creature in fado forest
<br>- Zinnia, Calla, Lobelia and Periwinkle hint which nearby quests you still need to start (that fit your level) 

<br><b>*other*</b>
<br>- added /profile <name> to open the webprofile of a character
<br>- reworked the in-game spam protection
<br>- admin command (*) inspect includes Java class name

<br><b>*website*</b>
<br>- Navigation box shows number of unread messages after login
<br>- Statistics on number of active accounts and characters

<br><b>*client*</b>
<br>- private messages are shown in their own tab in addition to the main chat log
<br>- new images for cherub and golden trees
<br>- users can reorder items in bag and chests
<br>- prefer user owned items when trying dragging from under other players
<br>- added a new outfit

<br><b>*note to forks*</b>
<br>- UpdateSigner now looks for a parameter keystore.update-alias instead of keystore.alias

<p>
<b>1.00</b>
<br><b>First officially stable release :)</b>

<br>- lots of testing
<br>- nice descriptions for many NPCs
<br>- fixed map bugs
<br>- added social buttons to website 

<p>
<b>0.99</b>
<br><b>*world*</b>
<br>- bridal outfit includes a veil
<br>- admin names are anonymised in support answer
<br>- many more outside zones with lighting
<br>- producers npcs tell the player how long a task will take before starting it
<br>- scroll eraser which cleans empty scrolls as a rare drop from some wizards
<br>- Inactive: New achievements for the weekly item quest
<br>- outfit image improvements, more depth and differentiation of some duplicates
<br>- allow pushing of players with items under them by moving the items with the player
<br>- alternative dreamscape map (on rotation)
<br>- introducing new NPC Marie<br>-Henri in Ados library
<br>- dry grass at mountain areas
<br>- include ATK and DEF to the player strenght calculation when checking if attacking is allowed
<br>- corpse owner timer of protected corpses is restarted when the corpse is moved

<br><b>*fixes*</b>
<br>- allow Supplies for Phalk to be continued if the special armor or cloak was accidentally sold

<br><b>*client*</b>
<br>- Animated blends are much faster than before
<br>- A menu item for taking screenshots
<br>- Bleach mode supports colored light
<br>- Blend layers can use any available blend mode

<p><b>0.98</b>

<br><b>*client*</b>
<br>- Zones can be colored according to hour, and otherwise
<br>- Outfit dialog resets to current outfit, when opened
<br>- Three new outfits available
<br>- Relative zone danger level is shown below the map

<br><b>*world*</b>
<br>- Garlic grows in the Kalavan City Gardens
<br>- Introducing new NPC Rachel in Ados bank
<br>- Kalavan City houses and Athor holiday apartments have usable tables now
<br>- Fado hotel beergarden style changed a bit
<br>- Reworked Ados interiors in some houses
<br>- Ados Bank got more bank chests
<br>- Semos and Ados mountain got more vegetation
<br>- Semos Mine Town Revival weeks ended
<br>- Athor cocktail bar got a new style
<br>- Ortiv Milquetoast interior reworked
<br>- Semos mine maps at level -2 got a new ground style
<br>- New Guess Kills quest in Nalwor City with new NPC, Crearid
<br>- New fruits which can be collected around Faiumoni (bananas, grapes, pomegranate, watermelons)
<br>- Coralia needs some fruit for her hat in a new quest

<br><b>*fixes*</b>
<br>- Farmer achievement can be reached due to garlic grower implementation
<br>- Stop player vs player attack if either player move into a protection zone
<br>- Fixed descriptions for items that can be picked 

<p><b>0.97</b>

<br><b>* Revival Weeks*</b>
<br>- Faiumonis inhabitans are excited for the Mine Town Revival Weeks already and decorated Semos City and the Mine Town area
<br>- Caroline finally found her way to the Mine Town for selling snacks and drinks
<br>- NPCs and games have been moved in relation to the former years 

<br><b>*world*</b>
<br>- More Semos NPCs help players now if they need some advise of what to do next
<br>- The duration of special outfits is now based on online time
<br>- More minimum levels for items
<br>- Semos inhabitants decided to open the new palisade wall a bit and added a new way to the south and west
<br>- Semos city tavern/INN owners rebuild their front garden and made it quite comfortable
<br>- New playground next to Plink at Semos_Plains_n
<br>- Creatures of Kikareukin changed their environment on level 4 and 5
<br>- Some mountain maps in Semos and Ados mountains changed their look
<br>- Semos Mine Town map has a new look: the tower is gone and a new miner hut built up
<br>- New achievements active: mainio armor set "Excellent Stuff", harvest vegetables and become a "Farmer"

<br><b>*website*</b>
<br>- New coloured outfits can be seen on the website

<br><b>*client*</b>
<br>- Outfit parts can be coloured
<br>- Dialogs can be closed by pressing ESC
<br>- Buddies can be invited to group directly from the buddy list
<br>- Other players can be invited to group via right click menu

<br><b>*fixes*</b>
<br>- Fixed descriptions for Ketteh Wehoh
<br>- Fixed quest history for MedicineForTad and mentions new place of Tad in Semos Village
<br>- Fixed some spaces which went into Tads dialogue
<br>- Fixed missing collision in Semos ciy with rebuilding the palisade wall
<br>- Blood on gates can't block these anymore
<br>- Login dialog gets re<br>-enabled after a failed login
<br>- Players can not attack others from protected areas
<br>- Working on some maps fixed layer errors
<br>- Decreased number of sheep to eight in Semos city (they were starving before)


<br><b>*internal code changes*</b>
<br>- table itemid was replaced with table item.

<p><b>0.96</b>
<br><b>*world*</b>
<br>- Barbarus moved his work place a bit closer to the Mines entrance and reduced the pick price to 400 money each
<br>- Haunchy Meatoch is really thankful for the help he gets each time from players and gives them some XP now
<br>- various animal pens have gates now. Also wolves in the park are behind a gate
<br>- Semos has a palisade wall now to protect the city against the creatures outside
<br>- there is a nice new beer garden in front of the Fado hotel
<br>- Tad moved to Semos Hostel and Ketteh Wehoh, in the town hall, will remind about his quest
<br>- the quest log hints if a quest which has been started isn't suitable for the current level
<br>- danger signs are more prominent

<br><b>*website*</b>
<br>- added an interactive Atlas to the website
<br>- improvements to the arianne.sourceforge.net website including an rss feed
<br>- achievements for Semos and Ados daily quests are in their own categories

<br><b>*client*</b>
<br>- support and tutorial textboxes stay on top
<br>- Atlas command now focuses on the current position
<br>- added Beginner's guide to help menu
<br>- healing messages don't spam the chat log anymore (but can be enabled in the setting dialog)
<br>- "where" command in the group menu

<br><b>*fixes*</b>
<br>- fixed kill enemy army quest (load again + added madaram archer and windwalker to kill<br>-list)
<br>- harold now understands plural words properly

<p><b>0.95</b>
<br>If you package Stendhal or have forked your own game based on it
<br>read https://stendhalgame.org/wiki/Automatic_Software_Updater

<br>- rewrote the updater so that it will not break onces a year anymore because the certificate expires
<br>- on Unix/Linux the home folder now defaults to $HOME/.config/stendhal for new installs
<br>- improved the best player score for low level players: https://stendhalgame.org/wiki/Fixing_RP_Score_2011

<br><b>* Marauroa*</b>
<br>- updated to Marauroa 3.8.7 which greatly improves server side performance

<br><b>*client*</b>
<br>- text boxes are now attached to the bottom of the screen
<br>- renamed the stendhal-FULL-0.xx.zip to stendhal-0.xx.zip. 
  the extra client without sound made sense a long time ago
  when the full client had twice the size of the soundless client.

<br><b>*world*</b>
<br>- John and Jane on Athor island have a disrupted holiday
<br>- Andy, at Ados cemetery, seeks revenge
<br>- Harold pays owed earnings instantly on start of dialogue



<br><b>*fixes*</b>
<br>- fixed not showing zone achievements
<br>- fixed webstart which did not work on the most recent OpenJDK version (Ubuntu 11.04, SuSE)

<p><b>0.94</b>
<br>- new achievements active: interior zones, DM points, completed quests, red armor set
<br>- increased time for expired items and earnings on the market at Harold
<br>- over<br>-eating clears the food list and makes the player sick, instead of killing them
<br>- empty corpses are not automatically inspected
<br>- NPCs who await a specific response (e.g. for a question) have a special icon

<br><b>*bugfixes*</b>
<br>- fixed right clicking on sources, fishing spots, etc.
<br>- On Mac cmd+dragging opens the item split window
<br>- client error log now works in the webstart client, too
<br>- a number of small map fixes

<br><b>*admin*</b>
<br>- added new zone int_abstract_admin_investigation for investigation of account issues
<br>- added new zone int_abstract_server_down for operating Stendhal on a read only database copy

<br><b>*website*</b>
<br>- achievements on character pages now have a mouse over box
<br>- nicer layout for chat logs and log selection
<br>- improved performance of Recent Events page
<br>- improved performance of pages with many images

<p><b>0.93</b>

<br><b>*world*</b>
<br>- added ghost hound (rare) to Semos mountain cemetery
<br>- Imorgen and her mother Mircea moved into a house in Fado forest
<br>- deathmatch creature spawn time dependent on player level and (inversely) on number of players in ring
<br>- get fresh water at some hidden new springs
<br>- Kill Enemy Army quest history with more detail and records number of completions
<br>- Xhiphin Zohos is thirsty and asks for water 
<br>- decorated Semos for Easter
<br>- Easter Bunny drops small easter eggs as he walks

<br><b>*features*</b>
<br>- Easter Bunny launchable via script
<br>- corpse auto inspect mode in settings panel
<br>- inspected corpses auto close when empty
<br>- corpse window title is the dead creature / player
<br>- corpses cannot be thrown far by other players if they're protected

<br><b>*website*</b>
<br>- new rankings for best player and hall of fame using achievements
<br>- My & My Friends view shows true rankings
<br>- support for special achievements from one off events

<br><b>*fixes*</b>
<br>- Ambers way changed a bit for holding her back from Aldrin
<br>- Jef answers to all keywords now he has information for
<br>- death penalty rounded before application and reported as suitable precision to player
<br>- daily/weekly quests are restarted immediately when aborted
<br>- daily monster quest creature to kill can't be requested again by Mayor if it was aborted this time
<br>- fix buying daisies seeds
<br>- improvements in understanding item names when talking with merchandizers, e.g. "solid plate shields"
<br>- fixed "porcino" singular and made NPC parser understand (some) misspelled words like "porcinis"
<br>- non<br>-exact answer matching in the fishermans license quiz
<br>- recognise the expressions "ice cream" and "teddy bear"
<br>- fix display texts for "ice cream"
<br>- Alrak and Pequod give the bobbin/oil directly when saying 'make' (as well as 'remind') if item is ready
<br>- fix a memory hole in the market

<p><b>0.92</b>

<br><b>*features*</b>
<br>- achievements system with notification in game of reached achievement and website integration
<br>- group system for sharing loots and chatting
<br>- show Production activity in the Travel Log
<br>- settings dialog for sound, clickmode, decorative fonts

<br><b>*world*</b>
<br>- sheep growing quest from Nishiya
<br>- Help Jef by finding his mom, Amber, in a new quest
<br>- Caroline moved into her refurbished house in Ados 
<br>- the required item to collect (if chosen from a list) is displayed in more quest histories
<br>- message about where you died, on death
<br>- sound on level up
<br>- configurable archer range: orc spearman can throw further
<br>- damage type of the arrows is used for archer players
<br>- player killers pay more to get healed by NPCs
<br>- NPCs who can list what produced items are available in the world. Katerina and Alice Farmer are examples

<br><b>*client*</b>
<br>- character selection screen has a grid layout
<br>- a GUI to aid group management
<br>- better multi-monitor behaviour

<br><b>*fixes*</b>
<br>- numerous small gui code fixes
<br>- all defined achievements can now be reached
<br>- simplified chest syncing to remove flicker
<br>- NPC conversation with improved and unified responses of producers and merchandisers
<br>- improved server side performance by changing Creature.getArea() to not create lots and lots of short lived objects

<p><b>0.91</b>

<br><b>*world*</b>
<br>- full health bonus when you level up
<br>- support answers via postman are orange
<br>- Caroline (daughter of Fritz) is at Ados market
<br>- greeting of NPCs by name
<br>- NPCs can hear at different distances (e.g. you need to get closer to Harold but you can be further from the DM assistant)
<br>- Stefan and Damon attend the Fado hotel
<br>- progress log which opens in a separate window, giving detailed information about open and closed quests
<br>- quest to help Anastasia's sick son

<br><b>*fixes*</b>
<br>- add buddies only once to the buddy list and display their canonical name
<br>- removing buddies who weren't on your list gives correct message
<br>- Herbs for Carmen quest simplified
<br>- word list improvements
<br>- NPC text matching improvements

<p><b>0.90.1</b>
<br>- fixed a bug which prevented logging in without at least one saved profile

<p><b>0.90</b>

<br><b>*world*</b>
<br>- quest for Ortiv Milquetoast in Kirdneh River House
<br>- Gaston, a Rat chef in Rat City bakery that will prepare the best crepes suzette au chocolate in town
<br>- Erna lends kitchen equipment
<br>- Karl sells sacks, Philomena sells butter
<br>- Elisabeth and her mother Carey found their way to Kirdneh
<br>- quest Chocolate For Elisabeth on Kirdneh playground
<br>- Semos is decorated for Christmas
<br>- Santa is visiting (and can now be made to leave after Christmas on time)
<br>- changed corpse protection logic to be fairer
<br>- Katerina and Jynath both heal at same price (they compromised on price, to have two locations of equally cheap healing)

<br><b>*fixes*</b>
<br>- Wikipedian follows redirects
<br>- positioning of entities to fix character position, attacking circles, creature placement errors
<br>- vaults and adventure island correctly flagged as interior zones so players shouldn't land in the wrong zone
<br>- fixed some fish sources in amazon
<br>- 70% of FindBugs warnings and most of all Eclipse warnings fixed
<br>- all tests now pass using the Eclipse JUnit plugin

<p><b>See <a href="http://arianne.cvs.sourceforge.net/viewvc/*checkout*/arianne/stendhal/doc/CHANGES.txt">all past changes</a></b>

<p><b>0.89</b>

<br><b>*features*</b>
<br>- quantity selector for control-drop
<br>- corpses have resistance
<br>- scrolls can be labelled with /markscroll command
<br>- cancel client download if the user closes the progress bar window and confirms the dialog
<br>- corpses have loot protection to anyone but the defender of the hits for a short time after death

<br><b>*world*</b>
<br>- Eheneumniranin, a half<br>-elf that lost his memories. He harvests the grain field in ados forest farm area
<br>- Gertha and Martha in Kalavan city gardens, they'll bake delicious apple and cherry pies
<br>- Wrviliza, a kobold barmaid in Wo'fol bar, she also provide new drinks (mild and strong koboldish torcibud)
<br>- Kormic, a kobold regular in Wo'fol bar
<br>- Uncle Dag in Ados market, he runs a distillery stand there and produces fierywater
<br>- Gaston, a Rat chef in Rat City bakery 
<br>- quest in Wo'fol (the reward is V.S.O.P. koboldish torcibud)
<br>- artichoke, garlic, mandragora (a magical herb) and zantedeschia (a flower) and cane fields are growing in Faiumoni
<br>- hen nests spawn eggs
<br>- new types of empty bottles
<br>- sickles can be used to harvest sugar cane
<br>- a new fish<br>-source on Amazon island
<br>- red lionfish can be sold on the Athor ferry
<br>- ados swamp and surroundings has a new landscape
<br>- Bobby, a small boy in Fado, waits for some visitors
<br>- scrying orbs around the deathmatch arena
<br>- dead gnarled and twisted trees and bushes in the Orcs pit

<br><b>*code*</b>
<br>- fixed calculation of player ages (it assumed that a second was 3*300ms)
<br>- all NPCs defined with a zone configurator (standardisation across code)
<br>- old style quests refactored to use standard conditions and actions
<br>- drawing of the ground layers sped up

<p><b>0.88</b>

<br><b>*features*</b>
<br>- right click on a player to start trading with them using a GUI
<br>- corpse and chest windows raise themselves if one with an already open window is inspected
<br>- buddies are sorted first by online status, then by name
<br>- don't reset to townhall on minor releases
<br>- deathmatch assistant announces completion and player can directly claim victory

<br><b>*world*</b>
<br>- new NPC Andy in Ados near the church
<br>- new NPC Haunchy Meatoch on Ados market with a new quest
<br>- new NPC Florence Boullabaisse on Ados market who will make a tasty Fish Soup for you
<br>- new NPC Fritz on Ados market
<br>- new NPC Barbarus in Semos Mine
<br>- new NPC Ortiv Milquetoast in Kirdneh River House 
<br>- new music in Orril Castle
<br>- new items fish soup, garlic, grilled steak, coal, pick, red lionfish
<br>- coal sources for extracting coal
<br>- added garlic to Sues sales list
<br>- new game for Semos Mine Town Revival Weeks: 9 switches
<br>- Mayor Chalmers enlisted the Pied Piper to help with the rat problem

<br><b>*website*</b>
<br>- animated/large NPCs like tomi and vulcanus now have an image
<br>- display ranks on character page 

<p><b>0.87.1</b>
<br>- fixed issue making client unresponsive for Windows users

<p><b>0.87</b>
<br><b>*world*</b>
<br>- NPCs have an 'ear' icon when they are attending a player
<br>- private messages can't be sent to an /away player - use postman
<br>- players returning from /away automatically get stored postman messages sent to them
<br>- own pets and sheep drawn on minimap
<br>- hoeing NPC in Semos Plains North East
<br>- added new NPC Marla to Ados
<br>- added some new descriptions to NPCs

<br><b>*website*</b>
<br>- read postman messages to and from your characters
<br>- redesign character page layout, with equipment arranged like in stendhal client
<br>- 'Recent Events' shows what has been happening in the world
<br>- added mouse over tips for items and monsters

<br><b>*client*</b>
<br>- Game screen ported to swing
<br>- Drag and drop drawn to a layer above everything
<br>- Bag, character, keyring and settings moved out of the game screen

<br><b>*code*</b>
<br>- improved performance of pathfinder
<br>- use external program for twitter access instead of disabled http basic auth API

<p><b>0.86.1</b>
<br><b>*bugfixes*</b>
<br>- If floating windows were saved under settings panel, move them on login
<br>- updater package does not use DefaultGameProperties, only use properties file, to make it easier for other projects to understand how to use updater without breaking it
<br>- use new 0.86.1 base for updater due to problems with webstart clients from 0.85
<br>- remove db_id entries from buddy list
<br>- offer deletion of update files in case of a security exception

<p><b>0.86</b>
<br><b>*world*</b>
<br>-new quest at the wizards tower in semos mountain
<br>-new music by semos dungeon, in semos and ados townhall, semos temple, ados church and in the forest
<br>-new sounds on the athor ship, in the ados sewers, at the ados city haven and some minor additions
<br>-Ados and Fado churches ring their bells at full and half hours
<br>-initial Hayunn dialog/tutorial streamlined and improved
<br>-Diogenes tells you about postman, he recently remembered that used to be his job
<br>-a sign at the flowers field which shows the meaning of these flowers
<br>-marked path from semos to ados city and to the athor ferry pier on ados coast
<br>-new npc added to ados market, who buys blue shield 
<br>-Simon in Ados church offers helpful guidance
<br>-blackjack max stake raised to 400
<br>-bakers want more button mushrooms

<br><b>*client*</b>
<br>-attack targets drawn as circles
<br>-settings panel uses icons and is always visible
<br>-new help menus for settings panel
<br>-"Remove account" button moved next to the account list
<br>-right click and ignore a player, or right click and unignore an already ignored player
<br>-/storemessage <player> <message> for using postman
<br>-karma scale bar (activated by asking Sarzina)

<br><b>*bugfixes*</b>
<br>-walkblocker tables have proper resistance
<br>-Mac OSX cmd key mapping
<br>-getting an amulet when killing thing

<br><b>*code*</b>
<br>-portals can do actions 
<br>-Messages from NPCs to offline players for postman can be stored in a table (without postman online)
<br>-SBoxLayout supports alignment and padding
<br>-support messages will get sent using postman if the player was offline
<br>-postman uses an admin action to store messages in table

<p><b>0.85</b>
<br><b>*features*</b>
<br>- all gui components use a new wood panel theme (even ones which did not have wood before)
<br>- character selection dialog after account login
<br>- login profiles can be cleaned up
<br>- right click and 'Where' yourself
<br>- /listproducers command for working NPCs
<br>- quest to help Phalk with food and clothes
<br>- slow down when walking over resisting entities
<br>- take resistance into consideration when choosing path
<br>- use more karma at the well and count activities
<br>- added descriptions to some npcs
<br>- new npc in ados church
<br>- new tutorial messages for receiving items and private messages
<br>- rats in semos village are not cowards

<br><b>*code*</b>
<br>- players can't use npc names or creature names
<br>- cannot add buddy who doesn't exist
<br>- refactored Kanmararn Soldiers quest
<br>- style code completely rewritten as a swing look & feel, and extended to all components used by stendhal
<br>- a script for calculating item drop rarities
<br>- quests history refactored to not use xml
<br>- many semos npcs reverted to not use xml for configuration
  
<br><b>*bugfixes*</b>
<br>- upper part of grain is not counted as grain (can move between grain fields)
<br>- raid creatures no longer have attack weakest profile even if the creature normally would
<br>- weekly item quest xp reward
<br>- quest completed check where completed state is set to other than 'done'
<br>- initial Hayunn dialog/tutorial cleaned up

<p><b>0.84</b>
<br><b>*features*</b>
<br>- new quest from Balduin if you have completed all other quests to get or collect rare weapons
<br>- daily and weekly item quests can ask for more than one of each item at once
<br>- eating, poisoned, grumpy and away status are shown in the stats panel
<br>- Dr. Feelgood can heal pets
<br>- Zoo Food quest is repeatable and food item request is randomised
<br>- pizza delivery missions selected by level
<br>- client can be started with username and password as parameters to bypass login gui (not for use on multi-user systems)
<br>- an arrow effect drawn for distance attacks
<br>- mrotho and diehelm brui sell arrows (and merenwen pays a bit less for arrows)
<br>- sarzina sells mega potions
<br>- temporary bans can be made using /ban
<br>- reason for ban is visible to player
<br>- new missile, a fire shuriken

<br><b>*code*</b>
<br>- new simple layout manager to replace the abandoned pagelayout
<br>- reworked zone configurators for Kill Dark Elves quest and for Kill Spiders quest.
<br>- reworked Daily Monster quest NPC engine
<br>- reworked kill quests to not clear player's information about previous killed creatures:
<br>  - Daily Monster quest
<br>  - Kill Gnomes quest
<br>  - Kill Dhohr Nuggetcutter quest
<br>  - Clean Storage Space quest
<br>  - Club Of Thorns quest
<br>  - Meet Hayunn quest
<br>  - Sad Scientist quest
<br>- npc conditions and actions for randomised item collection quests
<br>- fixed bug with xp display after death
<br>- ranged attack bug fixes on using up last missile and throwing from 1 tile away
<br>- email address field may be left completely empty on account creation 
<br>- /inspect command output improved for viewing quests, karma, and coordinates

<br><b>*website*</b>
<br>- performance optimisation
<br>- bugfixes including player display on firefox
<br>- spouse of a married player is displayed 

<p><b>0.83</b>
<br><b>*features*</b>
<br>- Rat City extended
<br>- Find the Rat Children quest
<br>- some creatures have attack strategy choosing weakest opponent (e.g. dragons, military commanders, bosses)
<br>- Zynn Iwuhos has some maps on display in the library
<br>- Tab completion for online nick names works now without /who called before
<br>- orc spearman creature
<br>- /atlas /faq and /manual commands to open useful pages in browser
<br>- Harold tweets trades, the official stendhal server uses <a href="http://twitter.com/stendhaltrade">http://twitter.com/stendhaltrade</a>
<br>- magical damage types of weapons (fire, ice ...)
<br>- resistance/vulnerability of creatures to magical weapons (fire, ice, ...)
<br>- attack sweeps look different depending on the attack type
<br>- Haizen's maze has music near the exit
<br>- Plan a new route when a player following a path hits another entity
<br>- single click for most actions and contextual mouse cursors (use /clickmode if you prefer doubleclick)
<br>- sub-zone teleport restrictions
<br>- NPCs can respond to emote actions
<br>- fertile ground inside houses
<br>- zone changing using mouse is possible
<br>- a family of NPCs holidaying in Ados
<br>- more rats and zones for the Pied Piper quest

<br><b>*bugfixes*</b>
<br>- archer behaviour
<br>- zero value offers supported at market
<br>- Monogenes easier to use
<br>- kill spiders and dark elves quests check you killed creatures from those relevant areas
<br>- recover automatically from corrupted cache files
<br>- ghosts have low hp like intended
<br>- turns walking along a path are now smooth
<br>- using a portal from distance walks the player to the portal
<br>- the client can cope better with differing tile sizes

<br><b>*code*</b>
<br>- creatures xml split into smaller parts
<br>- attacks are now events
<br>- signs can show an image instead of 'You read: ' text, or a description
<br>- Charas Converter jar available to download

<br><b>*website*</b>
<br>- new domain stendhalgame.org
<br>- rss feeds


<p><b>Stendhal 0.82.1</b>
<br>- new command /clickmode to toggle between single click walking and double click walking
<br>- fixed movement to drop target (only Microsoft Windows was affected)
<br>- fixed /mute not being stored across restarts
<br>- fixed pets not ownable

<p><b>Stendhal 0.82</b>
<br><b>*features*</b>
<br>- single click movement
<br>- Easter Bunny
<br>- Pied Piper quest
<br>- open manual on key F1
<br>- added /volume support for sound
<br>- asynchronous database access
<br>- Kalavan orb
<br>- Sad Scientist quest
<br>- Dice Gambling prizes upgraded

<br><b>*admin*</b>
<br>- new /script AdminPortal.class
<br>- support answer contains the name of the asking player in the greeting

<br><b>*website*</b>
<br>- added detail view of news items on their own pages (with nice urls)
<br>- improvements to various icons
<br>- reorganisation and cleanup of http://arianne.sf.net

<br><b>*bug fixes*</b>
<br>- Carmen only asks for her quest if the player is at least level 2.
<br>- improved stability of the client in uncommon situations
<br>- stat changes that occurred during zone change (like losing xp on death) did not update the stats window.
<br>- click walking is now a lot smoother
<br>- fixed Harold telling players about expiring earnings every minute

<p><b>Stendhal 0.81.2</b>
<br><b>*bug fixes*</b>
<br>- fixed a crash on Linux using alsa (non pulse) audio drivers and Sun Java (not OpenJDK) 
  if all channels are in use by another application
<br>- fixed rare InvalidVersionExceptions in the network code on high latency connections 
  (for example for people living outside Europe to an server in Europe)
<br>- handle failure to load sprite images more gracefully
<br>- improved logging of uncaught exceptions 
<p>
0.81.2 contains the first results of the Client Quality Weeks. Thanks everyone for providing
your error log files and please continue to do so.

<p><b>Stendhal 0.81.1</b>
<br><b>*bug fixes*</b>
<br>- fixed an issue with 0 hp created by logging out while dying (thanks to Andrzej Kofanski)
<br>- prevent client crash on empty soundNameList
<br>- renamed admins.list to admins.txt to simplify installation on windows with hidden file name extensions
<br>- fixed a server side classpath issue
<br>- updated to Marauroa 3.5 to fix an issue with null-values in the timedate columns in gameEvents and account

<p><b>Stendhal 0.81</b>
<br><b>*features*</b>
<br>- player stats moved from the character window to the side panel
<br>- a dragbar for making the game screen smaller (handy for netbooks)
<br>- new quest from Ouchit with new NPC in ados forest
<br>- having multiple correct answers for a riddle now possible
<br>- athor labyrinth redrawn 
<br>- h2 database support
<br>- ignored players are drawn as black forms

<br><b>*bug fixes*</b>
<br>- numerous small map fixes
<br>- poorly organised tilesets reorganised
<br>- list quests output fixed
<br>- split grain field
<br>- show a long dash rather than a negative number for required xp for max level players
<br>- feedback on using portals and chests from too far away
<br>- fixed "Drag and drop sometimes misses slots and hits ground instead" (was for drag and drop onto same slot)
<br>- better reject message for inactive accounts
<br>- fixed leander stealing all the pizzas of a player who has failed the quest previously

<br><b>*code*</b>
<br>- sound system rewritten and using oggs 
<br>- more client refactoring

<br><b>*website*</b>
<br>- fixed a directory traversing vulnerability on http://arianne.sf.net
  (special thanks to Ed Milner for discovering and reporting it)
<br>- account history
<br>- adminlevel shown

<p><b>See <a href="http://arianne.cvs.sourceforge.net/viewvc/*checkout*/arianne/stendhal/doc/CHANGES.txt">all past changes</a></b>]]>
-->
  </changelog>
  <navigation-image name="raid65.png"/>
  <screenshots>
    <image name="MagicTower98.jpg"/>
    <image name="Stendhal98.jpg"/>
    <image name="Achievement_Stendhal98.jpg"/>
    <image name="raid20110105.jpg"/>
    <image name="raid65.png"/>
    <image name="20070522_stendhal.jpg"/>
    <image name="20070522_1_stendhal.jpg"/>
    <image name="20070522_2_stendhal.jpg"/>
    <image name="20070522_stendhal.jpg"/>
    <image name="20070414_stendhal.jpg"/>
    <image name="20070130_stendhal.jpg"/>
    <image name="20060903_stendhal.jpg"/>
    <image name="20060324_stendhal.jpg"/>
    <image name="20060303_stendhal.jpg"/>
    <image name="20060310_stendhal.jpg"/>
    <image name="20060304_stendhal.jpg"/>
    <image name="20051220_stendhal.jpg"/>
    <image name="20051023_stendhal.jpg"/>
  </screenshots>
  <files>
    <file type="client" name="stendhal-XXX.zip" suggest="true">
      <description>This file contains the stendhal client. Download this to play online.</description>
    </file>
    <file type="server" name="stendhal-server-XXX.zip">
      <description><![CDATA[This file contains the stendhal server files.<br>See <a href="https://stendhalgame.org/wiki/Host_a_Stendhal_Server">hosting information</a>.]]></description>
    </file>
    <file type="source" name="stendhal-XXX-src.tar.gz">
      <description><![CDATA[This file contains the source code to build stendhal.<br>See <a href="https://stendhalgame.org/wiki/Navigation_for_Stendhal_Builders_and_Hosters">build information</a>.]]></description>
    </file>
  </files>
  <servers>
    <server name="Game server" url="https://stendhalgame.org/"/>
  </servers>
  <authors>
    <entry name="kymara" url="http://www.ohloh.net/accounts/kymara"/>
    <entry name="Hendrik" url="http://www.ohloh.net/accounts/nhnb"/>
    <entry name="kiheru" url="http://www.ohloh.net/accounts/kiheru"/>
    <entry name="madmetzger" url="http://www.ohloh.net/accounts/madmetzger"/>
    <entry name="yoriy" url="http://www.ohloh.net/accounts/yoriy"/>
    <entry name="bluelads" url="http://www.ohloh.net/accounts/Bluelads99"/>
    <entry name="storyteller" url="http://www.ohloh.net/accounts/Storyteller"/>
    <entry name="laguz" url="http://www.ohloh.net/accounts/Laguz"/>
    <entry name="tigertoes" url="http://www.ohloh.net/accounts/tigertoes"/>
    <entry name="plassy" url="http://www.ohloh.net/projects/stendhal/contributors/"/>
    <entry name="durkham" url="http://www.ohloh.net/projects/stendhal/AstridSawatzky"/>
    <entry name="MartinF" url="http://www.ohloh.net/accounts/martinfuchs"/>
    <entry name="mort" url="http://www.ohloh.net/p/stendhal/contributors/15940771139175"/>
    <entry name="Miguel Angel Blanch Lardin" url="https://stendhalgame.org/wiki/User:MiguelAngelBlanchLardin"/>
    <entry name="Chad3f" url="http://www.ohloh.net/p/stendhal/contributors/15940771143729"/>
    <entry name="Steve I." url="https://stendhalgame.org/wiki/User:StephenIerodiaconou"/>
    <entry name="Kim Purnell Samoa" url=""/>
    <entry name="Danter" url="https://stendhalgame.org/wiki/User:Danter"/>
    <entry name="Laurent Soubrevilla" url=""/>
    <entry name="Hans Haggstrom" url="http://www.iki.fi/zzorn/"/>
    <entry name="Jonas aka Damosh" url=""/>
    <entry name="TheGeneral" url=""/>

  </authors>
</page>
