<?xml version='1.0'?>
<page name="stendhal" shortdescription="A multiplayer online adventures game">
  <updated date="2011-10-12"/>
  <version id="0.97"/>
  <status value="stable"/>
  <type value="game"/>
  <cssdoc url="css/stendhal.css"/>
  <rated>
<!-- broken link   
    <entry><![CDATA[
      <a href="http://happypenguin.org/show?stendhal"><img src="http://happypenguin.org/rateomatic?stendhal"></a>]]>    
    </entry> -->
    <entry>
      <![CDATA[<a href="http://freshmeat.net/projects/stendhal/"><img src="/images/fm_logo.png"></a>]]>    
    </entry>
<!-- broken link    <entry>
      <![CDATA[<a href="http://www.gamesites200.com/mpog/vote.php?id=1850"><img src="http://www.gamesites200.com/mpog/vote.gif" ALT="Paid and Free
MMORPG & MPOG" border="0"></a>]]>    
    </entry>-->
  <entry>
      <![CDATA[&nbsp;&nbsp; <script type="text/javascript" src="http://www.ohloh.net/projects/3711/widgets/project_users"></script>]]>
    </entry>

  </rated>
  <description><![CDATA[ 
Are you looking for adventure? Want to fight for riches?<br>
Develop yourself and your social standing? Meet new people?<br>
Do you want to be part of a brave new world?
<p/>
<a href="http://stendhalgame.org">Stendhal</a> is a fully fledged <b>multiplayer</b> online adventures game (MMORPG) developed using the Arianne game development system.
<p/>
Stendhal features a new, rich and expanding world in which you can explore towns, buildings, plains, caves and dungeons. <br>
You will meet NPCs and acquire tasks and quests for valuable experience and cold hard cash.<br>
Your character will develop and grow and with each new level up become stronger and better. With the money you acquire you can buy new items and improve your armour and weapons.<br>
And for the blood thirsty of you; satisfy your killing desires by roaming the world in search of evil monsters!
<p/>
Stendhal is totally platform independent, written using Java 1.5 and the Java2D environment.
<p/>
So what are you waiting for?! A whole new world awaits...]]>
  </description>
  <extended><![CDATA[
  <p/><h2>Want to help us?</h2>
  The game is right now <b>PLAYABLE</b> and <b>FUN</b>.<p/>
  We would really love to get your help <a href="http://stendhalgame.org/wiki/Navigation_for_Stendhal_Contributors">contributing</a> and if you are interested you can learn a lot more about Stendhal at <a href="http://stendhalgame.org/wiki/Stendhal">Stendhal's wiki</a>.

  <p/><h2>Play now!</h2>
  Just click on the button to play:
  <p/><a href="https://stendhalgame.org/account/mycharacters.html"><img src="/images/webstart.png" alt="Click here to play"></a>
  ]]>
  </extended>
  <manual url="http://stendhalgame.org/wiki/StendhalManual"/>  
  <changelog><![CDATA[

<b>0.97</b>

<br><b>* Revival Weeks*</b>
<br>- Faiumonis inhabitans are excited for the Mine Town Revival Weeks already and decorated Semos City and the Mine Town area
<br>- Caroline finally found her way to the Mine Town for selling snacks and drinks
<br>- NPCs and games have been moved in relation to the former years 

<br><b>*world*</b>
<br>- More Semos NPCs help players now if they need some advise of what to do next
<br>- The duration of special outfits is now based on online time
<br>- More minimum levels for items
<br>- Semos inhabitants decided to open the new palisade wall a bit and added a new way to the south and west
<br>- Semos city tavern/INN owners rebuild their front garden and made it quite comfortable
<br>- New playground next to Plink at Semos_Plains_n
<br>- Creatures of Kikareukin changed their environment on level 4 and 5
<br>- Some mountain maps in Semos and Ados mountains changed their look
<br>- Semos Mine Town map has a new look: the tower is gone and a new miner hut built up
<br>- New achievements active: mainio armor set "Excellent Stuff", harvest vegetables and become a "Farmer"

<br><b>*website*</b>
<br>- New coloured outfits can be seen on the website

<br><b>*client*</b>
<br>- Outfit parts can be coloured
<br>- Dialogs can be closed by pressing ESC
<br>- Buddies can be invited to group directly from the buddy list
<br>- Other players can be invited to group via right click menu

<br><b>*fixes*</b>
<br>- Fixed descriptions for Ketteh Wehoh
<br>- Fixed quest history for MedicineForTad and mentions new place of Tad in Semos Village
<br>- Fixed some spaces which went into Tads dialogue
<br>- Fixed missing collision in Semos ciy with rebuilding the palisade wall
<br>- Blood on gates can't block these anymore
<br>- Login dialog gets re<br>-enabled after a failed login
<br>- Players can not attack others from protected areas
<br>- Working on some maps fixed layer errors
<br>- Decreased number of sheep to eight in Semos city (they were starving before)


<br><b>*internal code changes*</b>
<br>- table itemid was replaced with table item.


<p><b>0.96</b>
<br><b>*world*</b>
<br>- Barbarus moved his work place a bit closer to the Mines entrance and reduced the pick price to 400 money each
<br>- Haunchy Meatoch is really thankful for the help he gets each time from players and gives them some XP now
<br>- various animal pens have gates now. Also wolves in the park are behind a gate
<br>- Semos has a palisade wall now to protect the city against the creatures outside
<br>- there is a nice new beer garden in front of the Fado hotel
<br>- Tad moved to Semos Hostel and Ketteh Wehoh, in the town hall, will remind about his quest
<br>- the quest log hints if a quest which has been started isn't suitable for the current level
<br>- danger signs are more prominent

<br><b>*website*</b>
<br>- added an interactive Atlas to the website
<br>- improvements to the arianne.sourceforge.net website including an rss feed
<br>- achievements for Semos and Ados daily quests are in their own categories

<br><b>*client*</b>
<br>- support and tutorial textboxes stay on top
<br>- Atlas command now focuses on the current position
<br>- added Beginner's guide to help menu
<br>- healing messages don't spam the chat log anymore (but can be enabled in the setting dialog)
<br>- "where" command in the group menu

<br><b>*fixes*</b>
<br>- fixed kill enemy army quest (load again + added madaram archer and windwalker to kill<br>-list)
<br>- harold now understands plural words properly

<p><b>0.95</b>
<br>If you package Stendhal or have forked your own game based on it
<br>read http://stendhalgame.org/wiki/Automatic_Software_Updater

<br>- rewrote the updater so that it will not break onces a year anymore because the certificate expires
<br>- on Unix/Linux the home folder now defaults to $HOME/.config/stendhal for new installs
<br>- improved the best player score for low level players: http://stendhalgame.org/wiki/Fixing_RP_Score_2011

<br><b>* Marauroa*</b>
<br>- updated to Marauroa 3.8.7 which greatly improves server side performance

<br><b>*client*</b>
<br>- text boxes are now attached to the bottom of the screen
<br>- renamed the stendhal-FULL-0.xx.zip to stendhal-0.xx.zip. 
  the extra client without sound made sense a long time ago
  when the full client had twice the size of the soundless client.

<br><b>*world*</b>
<br>- John and Jane on Athor island have a disrupted holiday
<br>- Andy, at Ados cemetery, seeks revenge
<br>- Harold pays owed earnings instantly on start of dialogue



<br><b>*fixes*</b>
<br>- fixed not showing zone achievements
<br>- fixed webstart which did not work on the most recent OpenJDK version (Ubuntu 11.04, SuSE)

<p><b>0.94</b>
<br>- new achievements active: interior zones, DM points, completed quests, red armor set
<br>- increased time for expired items and earnings on the market at Harold
<br>- over<br>-eating clears the food list and makes the player sick, instead of killing them
<br>- empty corpses are not automatically inspected
<br>- NPCs who await a specific response (e.g. for a question) have a special icon

<br><b>*bugfixes*</b>
<br>- fixed right clicking on sources, fishing spots, etc.
<br>- On Mac cmd+dragging opens the item split window
<br>- client error log now works in the webstart client, too
<br>- a number of small map fixes

<br><b>*admin*</b>
<br>- added new zone int_abstract_admin_investigation for investigation of account issues
<br>- added new zone int_abstract_server_down for operating Stendhal on a read only database copy

<br><b>*website*</b>
<br>- achievements on character pages now have a mouse over box
<br>- nicer layout for chat logs and log selection
<br>- improved performance of Recent Events page
<br>- improved performance of pages with many images

<p><b>0.93</b>

<br><b>*world*</b>
<br>- added ghost hound (rare) to Semos mountain cemetery
<br>- Imorgen and her mother Mircea moved into a house in Fado forest
<br>- deathmatch creature spawn time dependent on player level and (inversely) on number of players in ring
<br>- get fresh water at some hidden new springs
<br>- Kill Enemy Army quest history with more detail and records number of completions
<br>- Xhiphin Zohos is thirsty and asks for water 
<br>- decorated Semos for Easter
<br>- Easter Bunny drops small easter eggs as he walks

<br><b>*features*</b>
<br>- Easter Bunny launchable via script
<br>- corpse auto inspect mode in settings panel
<br>- inspected corpses auto close when empty
<br>- corpse window title is the dead creature / player
<br>- corpses cannot be thrown far by other players if they're protected

<br><b>*website*</b>
<br>- new rankings for best player and hall of fame using achievements
<br>- My & My Friends view shows true rankings
<br>- support for special achievements from one off events

<br><b>*fixes*</b>
<br>- Ambers way changed a bit for holding her back from Aldrin
<br>- Jef answers to all keywords now he has information for
<br>- death penalty rounded before application and reported as suitable precision to player
<br>- daily/weekly quests are restarted immediately when aborted
<br>- daily monster quest creature to kill can't be requested again by Mayor if it was aborted this time
<br>- fix buying daisies seeds
<br>- improvements in understanding item names when talking with merchandizers, e.g. "solid plate shields"
<br>- fixed "porcino" singular and made NPC parser understand (some) misspelled words like "porcinis"
<br>- non<br>-exact answer matching in the fishermans license quiz
<br>- recognise the expressions "ice cream" and "teddy bear"
<br>- fix display texts for "ice cream"
<br>- Alrak and Pequod give the bobbin/oil directly when saying 'make' (as well as 'remind') if item is ready
<br>- fix a memory hole in the market

<p><b>0.92</b>

<br><b>*features*</b>
<br>- achievements system with notification in game of reached achievement and website integration
<br>- group system for sharing loots and chatting
<br>- show Production activity in the Travel Log
<br>- settings dialog for sound, clickmode, decorative fonts

<br><b>*world*</b>
<br>- sheep growing quest from Nishiya
<br>- Help Jef by finding his mom, Amber, in a new quest
<br>- Caroline moved into her refurbished house in Ados 
<br>- the required item to collect (if chosen from a list) is displayed in more quest histories
<br>- message about where you died, on death
<br>- sound on level up
<br>- configurable archer range: orc spearman can throw further
<br>- damage type of the arrows is used for archer players
<br>- player killers pay more to get healed by NPCs
<br>- NPCs who can list what produced items are available in the world. Katerina and Alice Farmer are examples

<br><b>*client*</b>
<br>- character selection screen has a grid layout
<br>- a GUI to aid group management
<br>- better multi-monitor behaviour

<br><b>*fixes*</b>
<br>- numerous small gui code fixes
<br>- all defined achievements can now be reached
<br>- simplified chest syncing to remove flicker
<br>- NPC conversation with improved and unified responses of producers and merchandisers
<br>- improved server side performance by changing Creature.getArea() to not create lots and lots of short lived objects

<p><b>0.91</b>

<br><b>*world*</b>
<br>- full health bonus when you level up
<br>- support answers via postman are orange
<br>- Caroline (daughter of Fritz) is at Ados market
<br>- greeting of NPCs by name
<br>- NPCs can hear at different distances (e.g. you need to get closer to Harold but you can be further from the DM assistant)
<br>- Stefan and Damon attend the Fado hotel
<br>- progress log which opens in a separate window, giving detailed information about open and closed quests
<br>- quest to help Anastasia's sick son

<br><b>*fixes*</b>
<br>- add buddies only once to the buddy list and display their canonical name
<br>- removing buddies who weren't on your list gives correct message
<br>- Herbs for Carmen quest simplified
<br>- word list improvements
<br>- NPC text matching improvements

<p><b>0.90.1</b>
<br>- fixed a bug which prevented logging in without at least one saved profile

<p><b>0.90</b>

<br><b>*world*</b>
<br>- quest for Ortiv Milquetoast in Kirdneh River House
<br>- Gaston, a Rat chef in Rat City bakery that will prepare the best crepes suzette au chocolate in town
<br>- Erna lends kitchen equipment
<br>- Karl sells sacks, Philomena sells butter
<br>- Elisabeth and her mother Carey found their way to Kirdneh
<br>- quest Chocolate For Elisabeth on Kirdneh playground
<br>- Semos is decorated for Christmas
<br>- Santa is visiting (and can now be made to leave after Christmas on time)
<br>- changed corpse protection logic to be fairer
<br>- Katerina and Jynath both heal at same price (they compromised on price, to have two locations of equally cheap healing)

<br><b>*fixes*</b>
<br>- Wikipedian follows redirects
<br>- positioning of entities to fix character position, attacking circles, creature placement errors
<br>- vaults and adventure island correctly flagged as interior zones so players shouldn't land in the wrong zone
<br>- fixed some fish sources in amazon
<br>- 70% of FindBugs warnings and most of all Eclipse warnings fixed
<br>- all tests now pass using the Eclipse JUnit plugin

<p><b>0.89</b>

<br><b>*features*</b>
<br>- quantity selector for control-drop
<br>- corpses have resistance
<br>- scrolls can be labelled with /markscroll command
<br>- cancel client download if the user closes the progress bar window and confirms the dialog
<br>- corpses have loot protection to anyone but the defender of the hits for a short time after death

<br><b>*world*</b>
<br>- Eheneumniranin, a half<br>-elf that lost his memories. He harvests the grain field in ados forest farm area
<br>- Gertha and Martha in Kalavan city gardens, they'll bake delicious apple and cherry pies
<br>- Wrviliza, a kobold barmaid in Wo'fol bar, she also provide new drinks (mild and strong koboldish torcibud)
<br>- Kormic, a kobold regular in Wo'fol bar
<br>- Uncle Dag in Ados market, he runs a distillery stand there and produces fierywater
<br>- Gaston, a Rat chef in Rat City bakery 
<br>- quest in Wo'fol (the reward is V.S.O.P. koboldish torcibud)
<br>- artichoke, garlic, mandragora (a magical herb) and zantedeschia (a flower) and cane fields are growing in Faiumoni
<br>- hen nests spawn eggs
<br>- new types of empty bottles
<br>- sickles can be used to harvest sugar cane
<br>- a new fish<br>-source on Amazon island
<br>- red lionfish can be sold on the Athor ferry
<br>- ados swamp and surroundings has a new landscape
<br>- Bobby, a small boy in Fado, waits for some visitors
<br>- scrying orbs around the deathmatch arena
<br>- dead gnarled and twisted trees and bushes in the Orcs pit

<br><b>*code*</b>
<br>- fixed calculation of player ages (it assumed that a second was 3*300ms)
<br>- all NPCs defined with a zone configurator (standardisation across code)
<br>- old style quests refactored to use standard conditions and actions
<br>- drawing of the ground layers sped up

<p><b>0.88</b>

<br><b>*features*</b>
<br>- right click on a player to start trading with them using a GUI
<br>- corpse and chest windows raise themselves if one with an already open window is inspected
<br>- buddies are sorted first by online status, then by name
<br>- don't reset to townhall on minor releases
<br>- deathmatch assistant announces completion and player can directly claim victory

<br><b>*world*</b>
<br>- new NPC Andy in Ados near the church
<br>- new NPC Haunchy Meatoch on Ados market with a new quest
<br>- new NPC Florence Boullabaisse on Ados market who will make a tasty Fish Soup for you
<br>- new NPC Fritz on Ados market
<br>- new NPC Barbarus in Semos Mine
<br>- new NPC Ortiv Milquetoast in Kirdneh River House 
<br>- new music in Orril Castle
<br>- new items fish soup, garlic, grilled steak, coal, pick, red lionfish
<br>- coal sources for extracting coal
<br>- added garlic to Sues sales list
<br>- new game for Semos Mine Town Revival Weeks: 9 switches
<br>- Mayor Chalmers enlisted the Pied Piper to help with the rat problem

<br><b>*website*</b>
<br>- animated/large NPCs like tomi and vulcanus now have an image
<br>- display ranks on character page 

<p><b>0.87.1</b>
<br>- fixed issue making client unresponsive for Windows users

<p><b>0.87</b>
<br><b>*world*</b>
<br>- NPCs have an 'ear' icon when they are attending a player
<br>- private messages can't be sent to an /away player - use postman
<br>- players returning from /away automatically get stored postman messages sent to them
<br>- own pets and sheep drawn on minimap
<br>- hoeing NPC in Semos Plains North East
<br>- added new NPC Marla to Ados
<br>- added some new descriptions to NPCs

<br><b>*website*</b>
<br>- read postman messages to and from your characters
<br>- redesign character page layout, with equipment arranged like in stendhal client
<br>- 'Recent Events' shows what has been happening in the world
<br>- added mouse over tips for items and monsters

<br><b>*client*</b>
<br>- Game screen ported to swing
<br>- Drag and drop drawn to a layer above everything
<br>- Bag, character, keyring and settings moved out of the game screen

<br><b>*code*</b>
<br>- improved performance of pathfinder
<br>- use external program for twitter access instead of disabled http basic auth API

<p><b>0.86.1</b>
<br><b>*bugfixes*</b>
<br>- If floating windows were saved under settings panel, move them on login
<br>- updater package does not use DefaultGameProperties, only use properties file, to make it easier for other projects to understand how to use updater without breaking it
<br>- use new 0.86.1 base for updater due to problems with webstart clients from 0.85
<br>- remove db_id entries from buddy list
<br>- offer deletion of update files in case of a security exception

<p><b>0.86</b>
<br><b>*world*</b>
<br>-new quest at the wizards tower in semos mountain
<br>-new music by semos dungeon, in semos and ados townhall, semos temple, ados church and in the forest
<br>-new sounds on the athor ship, in the ados sewers, at the ados city haven and some minor additions
<br>-Ados and Fado churches ring their bells at full and half hours
<br>-initial Hayunn dialog/tutorial streamlined and improved
<br>-Diogenes tells you about postman, he recently remembered that used to be his job
<br>-a sign at the flowers field which shows the meaning of these flowers
<br>-marked path from semos to ados city and to the athor ferry pier on ados coast
<br>-new npc added to ados market, who buys blue shield 
<br>-Simon in Ados church offers helpful guidance
<br>-blackjack max stake raised to 400
<br>-bakers want more button mushrooms

<br><b>*client*</b>
<br>-attack targets drawn as circles
<br>-settings panel uses icons and is always visible
<br>-new help menus for settings panel
<br>-"Remove account" button moved next to the account list
<br>-right click and ignore a player, or right click and unignore an already ignored player
<br>-/storemessage <player> <message> for using postman
<br>-karma scale bar (activated by asking Sarzina)

<br><b>*bugfixes*</b>
<br>-walkblocker tables have proper resistance
<br>-Mac OSX cmd key mapping
<br>-getting an amulet when killing thing

<br><b>*code*</b>
<br>-portals can do actions 
<br>-Messages from NPCs to offline players for postman can be stored in a table (without postman online)
<br>-SBoxLayout supports alignment and padding
<br>-support messages will get sent using postman if the player was offline
<br>-postman uses an admin action to store messages in table

<p><b>0.85</b>
<br><b>*features*</b>
<br>- all gui components use a new wood panel theme (even ones which did not have wood before)
<br>- character selection dialog after account login
<br>- login profiles can be cleaned up
<br>- right click and 'Where' yourself
<br>- /listproducers command for working NPCs
<br>- quest to help Phalk with food and clothes
<br>- slow down when walking over resisting entities
<br>- take resistance into consideration when choosing path
<br>- use more karma at the well and count activities
<br>- added descriptions to some npcs
<br>- new npc in ados church
<br>- new tutorial messages for receiving items and private messages
<br>- rats in semos village are not cowards

<br><b>*code*</b>
<br>- players can't use npc names or creature names
<br>- cannot add buddy who doesn't exist
<br>- refactored Kanmararn Soldiers quest
<br>- style code completely rewritten as a swing look & feel, and extended to all components used by stendhal
<br>- a script for calculating item drop rarities
<br>- quests history refactored to not use xml
<br>- many semos npcs reverted to not use xml for configuration
  
<br><b>*bugfixes*</b>
<br>- upper part of grain is not counted as grain (can move between grain fields)
<br>- raid creatures no longer have attack weakest profile even if the creature normally would
<br>- weekly item quest xp reward
<br>- quest completed check where completed state is set to other than 'done'
<br>- initial Hayunn dialog/tutorial cleaned up

<p><b>0.84</b>
<br><b>*features*</b>
<br>- new quest from Balduin if you have completed all other quests to get or collect rare weapons
<br>- daily and weekly item quests can ask for more than one of each item at once
<br>- eating, poisoned, grumpy and away status are shown in the stats panel
<br>- Dr. Feelgood can heal pets
<br>- Zoo Food quest is repeatable and food item request is randomised
<br>- pizza delivery missions selected by level
<br>- client can be started with username and password as parameters to bypass login gui (not for use on multi-user systems)
<br>- an arrow effect drawn for distance attacks
<br>- mrotho and diehelm brui sell arrows (and merenwen pays a bit less for arrows)
<br>- sarzina sells mega potions
<br>- temporary bans can be made using /ban
<br>- reason for ban is visible to player
<br>- new missile, a fire shuriken

<br><b>*code*</b>
<br>- new simple layout manager to replace the abandoned pagelayout
<br>- reworked zone configurators for Kill Dark Elves quest and for Kill Spiders quest.
<br>- reworked Daily Monster quest NPC engine
<br>- reworked kill quests to not clear player's information about previous killed creatures:
<br>  - Daily Monster quest
<br>  - Kill Gnomes quest
<br>  - Kill Dhohr Nuggetcutter quest
<br>  - Clean Storage Space quest
<br>  - Club Of Thorns quest
<br>  - Meet Hayunn quest
<br>  - Sad Scientist quest
<br>- npc conditions and actions for randomised item collection quests
<br>- fixed bug with xp display after death
<br>- ranged attack bug fixes on using up last missile and throwing from 1 tile away
<br>- email address field may be left completely empty on account creation 
<br>- /inspect command output improved for viewing quests, karma, and coordinates

<br><b>*website*</b>
<br>- performance optimisation
<br>- bugfixes including player display on firefox
<br>- spouse of a married player is displayed 

<p><b>0.83</b>
<br><b>*features*</b>
<br>- Rat City extended
<br>- Find the Rat Children quest
<br>- some creatures have attack strategy choosing weakest opponent (e.g. dragons, military commanders, bosses)
<br>- Zynn Iwuhos has some maps on display in the library
<br>- Tab completion for online nick names works now without /who called before
<br>- orc spearman creature
<br>- /atlas /faq and /manual commands to open useful pages in browser
<br>- Harold tweets trades, the official stendhal server uses <a href="http://twitter.com/stendhaltrade">http://twitter.com/stendhaltrade</a>
<br>- magical damage types of weapons (fire, ice ...)
<br>- resistance/vulnerability of creatures to magical weapons (fire, ice, ...)
<br>- attack sweeps look different depending on the attack type
<br>- Haizen's maze has music near the exit
<br>- Plan a new route when a player following a path hits another entity
<br>- single click for most actions and contextual mouse cursors (use /clickmode if you prefer doubleclick)
<br>- sub-zone teleport restrictions
<br>- NPCs can respond to emote actions
<br>- fertile ground inside houses
<br>- zone changing using mouse is possible
<br>- a family of NPCs holidaying in Ados
<br>- more rats and zones for the Pied Piper quest

<br><b>*bugfixes*</b>
<br>- archer behaviour
<br>- zero value offers supported at market
<br>- Monogenes easier to use
<br>- kill spiders and dark elves quests check you killed creatures from those relevant areas
<br>- recover automatically from corrupted cache files
<br>- ghosts have low hp like intended
<br>- turns walking along a path are now smooth
<br>- using a portal from distance walks the player to the portal
<br>- the client can cope better with differing tile sizes

<br><b>*code*</b>
<br>- creatures xml split into smaller parts
<br>- attacks are now events
<br>- signs can show an image instead of 'You read: ' text, or a description
<br>- Charas Converter jar available to download

<br><b>*website*</b>
<br>- new domain stendhalgame.org
<br>- rss feeds


<p><b>Stendhal 0.82.1</b>
<br>- new command /clickmode to toggle between single click walking and double click walking
<br>- fixed movement to drop target (only Microsoft Windows was affected)
<br>- fixed /mute not being stored across restarts
<br>- fixed pets not ownable

<p><b>Stendhal 0.82</b>
<br><b>*features*</b>
<br>- single click movement
<br>- Easter Bunny
<br>- Pied Piper quest
<br>- open manual on key F1
<br>- added /volume support for sound
<br>- asynchronous database access
<br>- Kalavan orb
<br>- Sad Scientist quest
<br>- Dice Gambling prizes upgraded

<br><b>*admin*</b>
<br>- new /script AdminPortal.class
<br>- support answer contains the name of the asking player in the greeting

<br><b>*website*</b>
<br>- added detail view of news items on their own pages (with nice urls)
<br>- improvements to various icons
<br>- reorganisation and cleanup of http://arianne.sf.net

<br><b>*bug fixes*</b>
<br>- Carmen only asks for her quest if the player is at least level 2.
<br>- improved stability of the client in uncommon situations
<br>- stat changes that occurred during zone change (like losing xp on death) did not update the stats window.
<br>- click walking is now a lot smoother
<br>- fixed Harold telling players about expiring earnings every minute

<p><b>Stendhal 0.81.2</b>
<br><b>*bug fixes*</b>
<br>- fixed a crash on Linux using alsa (non pulse) audio drivers and Sun Java (not OpenJDK) 
  if all channels are in use by another application
<br>- fixed rare InvalidVersionExceptions in the network code on high latency connections 
  (for example for people living outside Europe to an server in Europe)
<br>- handle failure to load sprite images more gracefully
<br>- improved logging of uncaught exceptions 
<p>
0.81.2 contains the first results of the Client Quality Weeks. Thanks everyone for providing
your error log files and please continue to do so.

<p><b>Stendhal 0.81.1</b>
<br><b>*bug fixes*</b>
<br>- fixed an issue with 0 hp created by logging out while dying (thanks to Andrzej Kofanski)
<br>- prevent client crash on empty soundNameList
<br>- renamed admins.list to admins.txt to simplify installation on windows with hidden file name extensions
<br>- fixed a server side classpath issue
<br>- updated to Marauroa 3.5 to fix an issue with null-values in the timedate columns in gameEvents and account

<p><b>Stendhal 0.81</b>
<br><b>*features*</b>
<br>- player stats moved from the character window to the side panel
<br>- a dragbar for making the game screen smaller (handy for netbooks)
<br>- new quest from Ouchit with new NPC in ados forest
<br>- having multiple correct answers for a riddle now possible
<br>- athor labyrinth redrawn 
<br>- h2 database support
<br>- ignored players are drawn as black forms

<br><b>*bug fixes*</b>
<br>- numerous small map fixes
<br>- poorly organised tilesets reorganised
<br>- list quests output fixed
<br>- split grain field
<br>- show a long dash rather than a negative number for required xp for max level players
<br>- feedback on using portals and chests from too far away
<br>- fixed "Drag and drop sometimes misses slots and hits ground instead" (was for drag and drop onto same slot)
<br>- better reject message for inactive accounts
<br>- fixed leander stealing all the pizzas of a player who has failed the quest previously

<br><b>*code*</b>
<br>- sound system rewritten and using oggs 
<br>- more client refactoring

<br><b>*website*</b>
<br>- fixed a directory traversing vulnerability on http://arianne.sf.net
  (special thanks to Ed Milner for discovering and reporting it)
<br>- account history
<br>- adminlevel shown

<p><b>See <a href="http://arianne.cvs.sourceforge.net/viewvc/*checkout*/arianne/stendhal/doc/CHANGES.txt">all past changes</a></b>]]>
  </changelog>
  <screenshots>
    <image name="raid65.png"/>
    <image name="20070522_stendhal.jpg"/>
    <image name="20070522_1_stendhal.jpg"/>
    <image name="20070522_2_stendhal.jpg"/>
    <image name="20070522_stendhal.jpg"/>
    <image name="20070414_stendhal.jpg"/>
    <image name="20070130_stendhal.jpg"/>
    <image name="20060903_stendhal.jpg"/>
    <image name="20060324_stendhal.jpg"/>
    <image name="20060303_stendhal.jpg"/>
    <image name="20060310_stendhal.jpg"/>
    <image name="20060304_stendhal.jpg"/>
    <image name="20051220_stendhal.jpg"/>
    <image name="20051023_stendhal.jpg"/>
  </screenshots>
  <files>
    <file type="binary" name="stendhal-XXX.zip">
      <description>This file contains the stendhal client. Download this to play online.</description>
      <os>
        <entry name="win32" status="100"/>
        <entry name="linux" status="100"/>
        <entry name="macosx" status="100"/>
      </os>
    </file>
    <file type="map editor binary" name="stendhal_mapeditor-2.00.zip">
      <description>This file contains the stendhal map editor. Download this to create new maps. Send them to us if you want them to appear on next releases. Use the tmx file format.</description>
      <os>
        <entry name="win32" status="100"/>
        <entry name="linux" status="100"/>
        <entry name="macosx" status="100"/>
      </os>
    </file>
    <file type="server script binary" name="stendhal-server-XXX.zip">
      <description>This file contains the stendhal server files. See http://stendhalgame.org/wiki/Host_a_Stendhal_Server</description>
      <os>
        <entry name="win32" status="100"/>
        <entry name="linux" status="100"/>
        <entry name="macosx" status="100"/>
      </os>
    </file>
    <file type="source" name="stendhal-XXX-src.tar.gz">
      <description>This file contains the source code to build stendhal. See http://stendhalgame.org/wiki/Stendhal#Build_information </description>
      <os>
        <entry name="win32" status="100"/>
        <entry name="linux" status="100"/>
        <entry name="macosx" status="100"/>
      </os>
    </file>
  </files>
  <servers>
    <server name="Game server" url="http://stendhalgame.org/"/>
  </servers>
  <authors>
    <entry name="kymara" url="http://www.ohloh.net/accounts/kymara"/>
    <entry name="Hendrik" url="http://www.ohloh.net/accounts/nhnb"/>
    <entry name="kiheru" url="http://www.ohloh.net/accounts/kiheru"/>
    <entry name="madmetzger" url="http://www.ohloh.net/accounts/madmetzger"/>
    <entry name="yoriy" url="http://www.ohloh.net/accounts/yoriy"/>
    <entry name="bluelads" url="http://www.ohloh.net/accounts/Bluelads99"/>
    <entry name="storyteller" url="http://www.ohloh.net/accounts/Storyteller"/>
    <entry name="laguz" url="http://www.ohloh.net/accounts/Laguz"/>
    <entry name="tigertoes" url="http://www.ohloh.net/accounts/tigertoes"/>
    <entry name="plassy" url="http://www.ohloh.net/projects/stendhal/contributors/"/>
    <entry name="durkham" url="http://www.ohloh.net/projects/stendhal/AstridSawatzky"/>
    <entry name="MartinF" url="http://www.ohloh.net/accounts/martinfuchs"/>
    <entry name="mort" url="http://www.ohloh.net/p/stendhal/contributors/15940771139175"/>
    <entry name="Miguel Angel Blanch Lardin" url="http://arianne.sourceforge.net/wiki/index.php/MiguelAngelBlanchLardin"/>
    <entry name="Chad3f" url="http://www.ohloh.net/p/stendhal/contributors/15940771143729"/>
    <entry name="Steve I." url="http://arianne.sourceforge.net/wiki/index.php/StephenIerodiaconou"/>
    <entry name="Kim Purnell Samoa" url=""/>
    <entry name="Danter" url="http://arianne.sourceforge.net/wiki/index.php/Danter"/>
    <entry name="Laurent Soubrevilla" url=""/>
    <entry name="Hans Haggstrom" url="http://www.iki.fi/zzorn/"/>
    <entry name="Jonas aka Damosh" url=""/>
    <entry name="TheGeneral" url=""/>

  </authors>
</page>
