<?xml version='1.0'?>
<website>
  <!--
  <item>
    <title></title>
    <date></date>
    <images> 
      <image url=""/>
    </images>
    <content>
      <![CDATA[]]>
      </content>
  </item>
  -->
  <item>
    <title>Stendhal 0.11 release: Monsters, dungeons and eXPerience</title>
    <date>Thu, 20 May 2005 14:28:23</date>
      <images> 
        <image url="screens/stendhal/THM_20050520_3_stendhal.jpg"/>
      </images>
    <content>
      <![CDATA[Another great release of Stendhal!. Don't get it wrong! This release is playable and fun. We just need to make the world bigger and add new monsters and here your collaboration is a MUST. Help us to create new levels and add new monsters and quests.<p>
        This release implements a better path finding, add more NPCs and a new level: dungeon.
        <br><b>-</b> Add Rat and Cave Rat entity
        <br><b>-</b> Added a balanced RP values
        <br>&nbsp;&nbsp;<b>*</b> ATK, DEF and HP values at <a href="http://stendhal.game-server.cc/StendhalCombatSimulation.xls">http://stendhal.game-server.cc/StendhalCombatSimulation.xls</a>
        <br>&nbsp;&nbsp;<b>*</b> Level values at <a href="http://stendhal.game-server.cc/StendhalLevelSimulation.xls">http://stendhal.game-server.cc/StendhalLevelSimulation.xls</a>
        <br><b>-</b> You gain XP by killing creatures and completing quests.
        <br><b>-</b> Add new Sheep GFX
        <br><b>-</b> Better Sheep AI and Creature AI
        <br><b>-</b> A map editor <a href="http://prdownloads.sourceforge.net/arianne/stendhal-mapeditor-0.01.zip?download">here</a>. Please help us create maps for stendhal ( maps shouldn't be bigger than 128x128 ). Use the existing maps or template as a way to learn. Your help makes Stendhal better!.

        <p>Finally the <a href="http://arianne.sourceforge.net/wiki/index.php/StendhalOpenTasks">tasks</a> written on the previous news item are still open and needing attention.<br>
        Also if you can write properly English we would really love help to write a game manual at <a href="http://arianne.sourceforge.net/wiki/index.php/StendhalManual">http://arianne.sourceforge.net/wiki/index.php/StendhalManual</a>.
         ]]>
    </content>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title>Stendhal 0.10 release</title>
    <date>Thu, 12 May 2005 13:56:23</date>
      <images> 
        <image url="screens/stendhal/THM_20050512_stendhal.jpg"/>
      </images>
    <content>
      <![CDATA[This new release of Stendhal adds very important features like:
        <br><b>-</b> Add wolf entity
        <br><b>-</b> Make real combat system
        <br><b>-</b> Creatures can die
        <br><b>-</b> Add new Sheep GFX
        <br><b>-</b> Better Sheep AI
        <br><b>-</b> Compiled map editor <a href="http://prdownloads.sourceforge.net/arianne/stendhal-mapeditor-0.00.zip?download">here</a>. Please help us create maps for stendhal ( maps shouldn't be bigger than 128x128 ). Use the existing maps as a way to learn. Your help makes Stendhal better!.

        <p>Finally the <a href="http://arianne.sourceforge.net/wiki/index.php/StendhalOpenTasks">tasks</a> written on the previous news item are still open and needing attention.<br>
        Also if you can write properly English we would really love help to write a game manual at <a href="http://arianne.sourceforge.net/wiki/index.php/StendhalManual">http://arianne.sourceforge.net/wiki/index.php/StendhalManual</a>.
         ]]>
    </content>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title>Major changes on Stendhal: combat implemented</title>
    <date>Sat, 07 May 2005 20:03:55</date>
      <images> 
        <image url="screens/stendhal/THM_20050507_stendhal.jpg"/>
      </images>
    <content>
      <![CDATA[A new week, almost a new release :)<br>I have added combat to Stendhal and HP bars, and a basic in game GUI.<br>Release should happen soon, exactly at the same moment I assign <i>coherent</i> RP values to entities.<p>
         Also the CVS code has been cleaned and refactored, so Client is now clearer than ever. If you plan to create a game using Arianne, Stendhal would be a great base for your client. :)<p>
         On the near future <i>(1 month or so)</i> I will stabilize Stendhal development and start again all the documentation process that means:
        <br><b>-</b> Document all the code.
        <br><b>-</b> Fix, update and improve Wiki Documents.
        <br><b>-</b> Complete <a href="http://arianne.sourceforge.net/wiki/index.php/StendhalDesign">Stendhal Design</a> document
        <br><b>-</b> Complete and release our new Stendhal book.
         ]]>
    </content>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title>Marauroa 0.95 and Stendhal 0.03 bug fixes release</title>
    <date>Thu, 28 Apr 2005 16:33:54</date>
    <content>
      <![CDATA[These are two small releases but very important in the development of Arianne.<p>
        On Marauroa we have fix a bug that has been there since 0.30 release and that was related to the way MySQL managed transactions, also we added a method to request synchronization from a unsynced client so you should expect now a better gameplay.<p>
        On Stendhal we have added A*, fixed a bug with Sheep weight due to signed/unsigned, improved Sheep movement, added Patrol and  follow path action, fixed collision detection area, changed Game Chat dialog so that it opens with Ctrl+L, NPC counts sheeps sold and bought, client reconnect on out of sync, a single text line is visible now, now combat icon is centered on the bottom right corner and finally optional collision detection boxes.<p>
        Out next steps are:
        <br><b>-</b> Add wolf entity
        <br><b>-</b> Make combat real
        <br><b>-</b> Add currency to game
        <br><b>-</b> Add new Sheep GFX
        <br><b>-</b> Initial character customization
        <p>Finally the tasks written on the previous news item are still open and needing attention.
         ]]>
    </content>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title>Stendhal 0.02 released: Sheeps and food</title>
    <date>Thu, 17 Apr 2005 13:21:01</date>
      <images> 
        <image url="screens/stendhal/THM_20050417_stendhal.jpg"/>
      </images>
    <content>
      <![CDATA[This is the first release of Stendhal that has the tag playable (PLAYABLE).<br> You can walk, chat, attack, buy and sell sheeps, change zones, request help, etc...<p>
         I am actually in need of someone with RP gaming experience that wants to help me to create a simple game system based on S6S and give correct values to entities values.<p>
         There are three open tasks that are of vital importance for Stendhal:
         <br><b>-</b> Create a game manual at <a href="http://arianne.sourceforge.net/wiki/index.php/StendhalManual">http://arianne.sourceforge.net/wiki/index.php/StendhalManual</a>
         <br><b>-</b> Define the entities RP values and the RP general guidelines, like how to attack, how fast, how fast to move, how is allowed to attack to, etc...</a>
         <br><b>-</b> Complete the manual about how to use Tiled to create maps for stendhal and add screenshots to it.</a>
         <p>Perhaps you would like to help us close some <a href="http://arianne.sourceforge.net/wiki/index.php/StendhalOpenTasks">tasks</a> related to Stendhal or review with us the <a href="http://arianne.sourceforge.net/wiki/index.php/StendhalDesign">design document</a>.<p>
         ]]>
    </content>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title>Marauroa 0.94 bug fixes release</title>
    <date>Wed, 17 Apr 2005 13:21:01</date>
    <content>
      <![CDATA[This release adds secure login feature as well as fixs a bug at JDBC Database class that didn't allowed a RPObject to be correctly stored.<p> 
         You have a complete step by step guide at <a href="http://arianne.sourceforge.net/wiki/index.php/HowToBuildMarauroa">http://arianne.sourceforge.net/wiki/index.php/HowToBuildMarauroa</a>
         ]]>
    </content>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title>Marauroa 0.93 bug fixes release</title>
    <date>Wed, 8 Apr 2005 20:31:01</date>
    <content>
      <![CDATA[A new emergency release of Marauroa that fix several important bugs, the main one is the 100% CPU usage due to multithread send feature.<p> 
         You have a complete step by step guide at <a href="http://arianne.sourceforge.net/wiki/index.php/HowToBuildMarauroa">http://arianne.sourceforge.net/wiki/index.php/HowToBuildMarauroa</a>
         ]]>
    </content>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title>Stendhal 0.01 released</title>
    <date>Thu, 5 Apr 2005 20:12:01</date>
      <images> 
        <image url="screens/stendhal/THM_20050405_stendhal.jpg"/>
      </images>
    <content>
      <![CDATA[Our second release of Stendhal, and again it is not intended to be playable (<b>NO PLAYABLE</b>). You can walk, chat, collide, move from one zone to another, talk to NPC, attack other players and our dummy, but it lacks of the quality to consider it playable.<p>
         This release also features a new map editor using <a href="http://tiled.rpgdx.net/index.html">Tiled</a> with a write only plugin to create Stendhal maps, on CVS you can access our actual maps and the tileset used to create them... help is appreciated to build bigger and better maps :) We also added a GUI to Stendhal that makes simpler to login to server, and there is a Java Webstart feature.<p>
	 We are working 110% on creating new GFX: samoa is creating a sheep and a wolf ( you can see it at Forums ).<br>
         Next steps are towards completing the RP system, and increasing the NPC interaction, and also fixing a strange bug that make game to work only sometimes ( most of them ).
         On the meanwhile you would like to help us close some <a href="http://arianne.sourceforge.net/wiki/index.php/StendhalOpenTasks">tasks</a> related to Stendhal or review with us the <a href="http://arianne.sourceforge.net/wiki/index.php/StendhalDesign">design document</a>.<p>
         There is still no public server for Stendhal...
         ]]>
    </content>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title>Marauroa 0.92 released</title>
    <date>Wed, 3 Apr 2005 20:31:01</date>
    <content>
      <![CDATA[This release changes some interfaces to suit in a better way the game development.<br>
         If you plan to use Marauroa, you should update to this release in order to get it working. Soon I will update the API guides to show these changes.<p>
         You have a complete step by step guide at <a href="http://arianne.sourceforge.net/wiki/index.php/HowToBuildMarauroa">http://arianne.sourceforge.net/wiki/index.php/HowToBuildMarauroa</a>
         ]]>
    </content>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title>Stendhal gets a GUI</title>
    <date>Mon, 7 Mar 2005 15:04:36</date>
      <images> 
        <image url="images/articles/stendhal_gui.jpg"/>
      </images>
    <content>
      <![CDATA[After a full weekend of work, I have added a GUI to Stendhal. It is a bit basic but useful enough to make the game playable.<p>
         Next step is about adding attack and heal actions and make multizone works in a more intuitive way.<br>The point is to add <i>*slowly*</i> new features to build a complete game as soon as possible. You can read the complete plan at our Wiki in <a href="http://arianne.sourceforge.net/wiki/index.php/StendhalObjectives">StendhalObjectives</a><br>
         BTW I keep begging for help to close these <a href="http://arianne.sourceforge.net/wiki/index.php/StendhalOpenTasks">tasks</a> :)<p>
         The most important task to complete now it 100% related to GFX; we do need new GFX as explained in the Stendhal tasks.
         ]]>
    </content>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title>Marauroa 0.91 released: critical bug fixes</title>
    <date>Wed, 3 Mar 2005 20:31:01</date>
    <content>
      <![CDATA[This release of Marauroa closes a few bug fixes that make server work abnormally: a bug at RPServerManager, a bug at PlayerEntryContainer and a important bug at RPWorld.<br>
         If you plan to use Marauroa, you should update to this release in order to get it working.<p>
         You have a complete step by step guide at <a href="http://arianne.sourceforge.net/wiki/index.php/HowToBuildMarauroa">http://arianne.sourceforge.net/wiki/index.php/HowToBuildMarauroa</a>
         ]]>
    </content>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title>Stendhal 0.00 released</title>
    <date>Mon, 1 Mar 2005 20:52:47</date>
      <images> 
        <image url="screens/stendhal/THM_20050303_stendhal.jpg"/>
      </images>
    <content>
      <![CDATA[This is the first relese of Stendhal. It is not intended to be playable (<b>NO PLAYABLE</b>), it is just a tech demo of where you can walk, collide and change of zone.<p>
         As you know we drive our development by the guideline:<i>release small, release often</i>. Now we will start the development of the GUI ( anyone wanna help? ) and the rest of actions to make it playable. In around 1 month the game could be really playable.<p>
         On the meanwhile you would like to help us close some <a href="http://arianne.sourceforge.net/wiki/index.php/StendhalOpenTasks">tasks</a> related to Stendhal or review with us the <a href="http://arianne.sourceforge.net/wiki/index.php/StendhalDesign">design document</a>.<br>
         I can't really handle all by myself :)
         ]]>
    </content>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title>Marauroa 0.90 released</title>
    <date>Wed, 19 Feb 2005 14:09:34</date>
    <content>
      <![CDATA[After more than six months we have at last another release of Marauroa.<br>
         This release sucessfully implements multizone features into Marauroa and has been splitted in several different packages: client, common and server.<br>
         Also this release features the new content streaming system that is being used in Stendhal.<p>
         This release is <font color=red>incompatible</font> with mapacman and gladiator. We are working to recover them as soon as possible.
        ]]>
    </content>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title>Stendhal: Player can move and collide with world</title>
    <date>Mon, 16 Feb 2005 10:10:13</date>
    <content>
      <![CDATA[As I said, development is showing some interesting results in a short period of time. The actual <i>client</i> allows the player to move and collide with objects that exists on world. Problem is that the client is a development work thing, and need to be refactored in order to be released, but I think that around 2 weeks could be something available.<p>AS preview, just a video: <a href="http://stendhal.game-server.cc/Stendhal_0.00_Video.avi">Stendhal 0.00 video</a> (24") 266KB]]>
    </content>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title>Stendhal development shows first results</title>
    <date>Sat, 29 Jan 2005 13:41:51</date>
      <images> 
        <image url="images/articles/THM_stendhal_003.jpg"/>
      </images>
    <content>
      <![CDATA[Stendhal is our next game to test the new exciting features in Arianne: multizones and content transfer. <p>The idea behind Stendhal is a small multiplayer action game very similar to Nintendo's Zelda.<br/> There is going to be no argument at all on it for a while, but it is a start to show that it works and works correctly.<p>Once the development is stabilized we are going to need new GFX, music and some people to write something like a plot for the game, but that time is still a bit far. <p> I will show more info when we have it working.]]>
    </content>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title>Big change coming in Marauroa</title>
    <date>Fri, 14 Jan 2005 14:27:16</date>
    <content>
      <![CDATA[Again, a few months without news of the development. Again, sorry. Development keeps moving and marauroa advances at a slow but constant speed. <br/>Waldemar ported all the code to Java 5.0 and I finally completed the change to multizone code. We both have changed the package structure of marauroa so that now it is clearer how to port it to J2ME or another language, as the server, client and commons parts are now independient packages.<p>On the client side, I will begin to write a new Java2D client for our new game, Stendhal, so I will not update ariannexp for a while.<br/> I will try also to post more news if I have spare time.]]>
      </content>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title>I am still here</title>
    <date>Wed, 11 Nov 2004 17:23:42</date>
    <content>
      <![CDATA[I am really sorry for being away so much time. During this 3 months development of Arianne has been idle. I am going to do my best to get the multizone feature working <i>(as it only needs testing and test cases to be written of them)</i>.<br>All the games have been taken down too because I have changed of computer and I prefer to move to the new Arianne. No timelines by now, but expect around january to see something interesting again. Sorry,<br>Miguel]]>
      </content>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title>Arianne's 5th birthday</title>
    <date>Sat, 28 Aug 2004 20:11:54</date>
    <content>
      <![CDATA[Arianne has reached the age of 5 years. The way has been hard and full of unproductive periods. The multizone feature is being added now and should be complete in 1-2 weeks allowing us the development
of Stendhal, which has already been started.<p/> Soon I will write more about it.]]>
      </content>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title>game servers are going to be down up to Aug, 15</title>
    <date>Thu, 03 Aug 2004 16:41:16</date>
    <content>
      <![CDATA[Hehehe, you know, holidays!, I will shutdown the computer that run that arianne's server up to Aug, 15.<br> We are still looking for a 24/7 hoster of our servers so we can avoid this situations.<p>As a follow up, our next game is going to be called Stendhal, surely around Aug, 15 you will be able to read more about it.]]>
      </content>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title>mapacman 1.00 released</title>
    <date>Wed, 28 Jul 2004 18:34:48</date>
      <images> 
        <image url="images/articles/mapacman_gui.jpg"/>
      </images>
    <content>
      <![CDATA[Thanks to the HUGE amount of bugs report about mapacman I have been able to do this release. Mainly I have fixed the issue that many of you pointed about GUI and I have recoded the GUI from scratch to meet the requirements.<br>
Also Many of you had problems with timeouts, so now mapacman 
doesn't handle timeouts, when you feel something is not working
press ESC and you will be returned to the previous screen.<p>
This released still miss the Create account from game feature
that may be added on the next release of marauroa: no promises.]]>
      </content>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title>mapacman 0.90 released: final release of mapacman</title>
    <date>Tue, 13 Jul 2004 17:23:25 GMT</date>
      <images> 
        <image url="screens/mapacman/THM_20040712_mapacman.jpg"/>
      </images>
    <content>
      <![CDATA[mapacman, our multiplayer online pacman clone, reaches its 0.90 version.
      <br/>This is the last release of mapacman because as you know our goal is to 
      create a real online multiplayer RPG and not a pacman game :)<p/>
      Now I will start working again on gladiators to make it a real game much like a
      simple Zelda clone. About if it is 2D or 3D is still to be decided, but it is prone
      that i finally goes after 2D because it is simpler to implement.<p/>
      This release features also a new ariannexp version that adds out of sync logic 
      support at the pyarianne side.]]>
      </content>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title>Marauroa 0.41 released</title>
    <date>Tue, 13 Jul 2004 00:45:12 GMT</date>
    <content>
      <![CDATA[This version of Marauroa is a bug fixes release over 0.40 version, that
       consolidate our work on RPClasses and per player synchronization. Also I have
       fixed a few bugs on the mapacman script so game will be better.<p/>This release
       creates base work for multizone system that will move us to Marauroa 1.0<br>As
       usual your bugs reports are appreciated. ]]>
      </content>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title>Our new website is up and running</title>
    <date>Fri, 09 Jul 2004 12:56:53 GMT</date>
    <content>
      <![CDATA[It has been around 6 months and our website got outdated again.<br/>
        So after hiring an artist for website creation guidelines we have come with 
        this design, that reuses mostly the previous website code<p/>
        Our goal has been to make the website clear, informative and easy to read, so 
        please share with us your opinion at the Forum so we can all together build a 
        better website for Arianne.]]>
      </content>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title>mapacman 0.10 released</title>
    <date>Tue, 06 Jul 2004 12:56:53 GMT</date>
      <images>
        <image url="screens/mapacman/THM_20040705_mapacman.jpg"/>
      </images>
    <content>
      <![CDATA[This version of mapacman features the new walls done by 
      zzorn and adds correct scrolling. You still need to create an account at 
      <a href="http://mapacman.game-server.cc">mapacman server</a>.<p>I still 
      need your bugs reports, as it is the only way of improving the game.]]>
    </content>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title>Marauroa 0.40 released</title>
    <date>Mon, 5 Jul 2004 13:09:37 GMT</date>
    <content><![CDATA[Marauroa is the arianne game server coded using Java and 
      Python.<br>This release is very important for us as it consolidate all 
      the development of the last 9 months on a very stable and advanced release
      that adds per player synchronization, correct delta^2 perception system, 
      classes of ingame objects and better python scripts.<p>I also remind that 
      the tutorial is now available at 
      <a href="http://arianne.sourceforge.net/wiki/HowToWriteGamesUsingArianne">
      Wiki</a>]]></content>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title>mapacman server will be down 24-48 hours</title>
    <date>Thu, 1 Jul 2004 12:56:13 GMT</date>
    <content><![CDATA[I will shutdown server to develop the next versions of both 
      marauroa and mapacman. They should be out before Monday.<p>Sorry for the 
      inconvenience.]]></content>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title>mapacman 0.03 released</title>
    <date>Tue, 18 Jun 2004 16:14:02 GMT</date>
    <content><![CDATA[This new version of mapacman features a bigger map, that is 
      around 8 times bigger than the 0.02 map, a scrollable view and new animations
       and graphics for mapacman done by zzorn. On server side there are some changes 
       on the way that will be released perhaps over July, 1. The most important 
       are RPClass is finally working as expected and mapacman code has been 
       optimized.]]></content>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title>mapacman 0.02 released</title>
    <date>Tue, 8 Jun 2004 20:11:02 GMT</date>
      <images> 
        <image url="screens/mapacman/THM_20040608_mapacman.jpg"/>
      </images>
    <content>
      <![CDATA[The bug about background clearing and the bug about TAB on the
      main screen were fixed. The player is now different than the rest of the pacmans,
      and they now have animations. You can see your score at the bottom of the screen.
      <br>By the way, take extra care with ghost it is too dangerous.<p>Next version of
      mapacman will feature a 10 times bigger map, more ghosts and a 
      ssssurprissssse]]></content>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title>Macro release!: Marauroa, ariannexp, gladiators and mapacman</title>
    <date>Fri, 4 Jun 2004 20:53:37 GMT</date>
    <content>
      <![CDATA[
        It has been a lot of work, but finally everything is up and running:<ul>
		<li><i>Marauroa 0.36</i> Real pacman support, improved the way password are 
		  stored in database, speeded up marauroa to make clients see their actions 
		  result sooner and added command line support for nullClient</li>
		<li><i>ariannexp 0.10.1 and pyarianne 0.10.1</i> Added compressed RPMap 
		  message support, improved autoconf and automake files and released a 
		  compiled version of pyarianne so you can develop your own games easily.</li>
		<li><i>Gladiators 0.08.5.3</i> Enjoy this one because it is the last version 
		  of Gladiators released. We are actually working hard to replace it with a 
		  python version of it that will work in a different way.</li>
		<li><i>mapacman 0.01</i> The first mapacman release. Please give it a try 
		  but don't eat the ghost :-)</li></ul>
		Also I have added a Tutorial about how to create games using Arianne, please 
		  post your questions about it on the Forum, so that working together we can 
		  make a great document.
      ]]>
      </content>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title>mapacman is running on linux</title>
    <date>Tue, 3 Jun 2004 16:03:24 GMT</date>
      <images> 
        <image url="screens/mapacman/THM_20040603_mapacman.jpg"/>
      </images>
    <content>
      <![CDATA[
		Although I were sure that it runs on Linux it is fun to see that it really does.<br>
		Here you can see the screenshot as taken by keiner. In a few days I hope to be able to 
		release a first version, that is, when I complete the GUI.<p>
		The HOWTO continue evolving into a great document at 
		<a href="http://arianne.sourceforge.net/wiki/HowToWriteGamesUsingArianne">
		http://arianne.sourceforge.net/wiki/HowToWriteGamesUsingArianne</a>
      ]]>
      </content>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title>mapacman is near 0.01</title>
    <date>Tue, 1 Jun 2004 01:05:41 GMT</date>
      <images> 
        <image url="screens/mapacman/THM_20040601_mapacman.jpg"/>
      </images>
    <content>
      <![CDATA[mapacman continues evolving.<br>Now it is able to render the original
        pacman map, but with the extra thing that each object in screen is an Arianne RPObject,
        so everything is handled by Python code on the server using real Arianne RPObjects. 
        We are using right now around 300 dots and 600 blocks representing walls. Turn times 
        continue scaling perfectly with around 50 ms used of a turn time of 600 ms.]]>
      </content>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title>Marauroa 0.35 and ariannexp 0.10.0 released</title>
    <date>Tue, 25 May 2004 21:48:32 GMT</date>
    <content>
      <![CDATA[
		Today a major step has been taken on the Arianne development. <br>
		ariannexp has reach it second iteration and finally pyarianne is also working on Linux.
 		So developing new clients and games is easier than ever, you can check it at Wiki at 
 		<a href="http://arianne.sourceforge.net/wiki/index.php/HowToWriteGamesUsingArianne">here</a>.<p>
		marauroa has also being released with this version featuring support for an initial mapacman 
		server side game and in a few days a version of mapacman client will be released.<p>
		I am very insterested on problems with ariannexp at linux side, and would be extremly 
		thanked if those problems are fixed as well.
      ]]>
      </content>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title>mapacman is progressing</title>
    <date>Tue, 18 May 2004 17:53:54 GMT</date>
      <images> 
        <image url="screens/mapacman/THM_20040517_mapacman.jpg"/>
      </images>
    <content>
      <![CDATA[
		No, mapacman is not vaporware. Simply that I don't have enough free time lately to work 
		on it as much as I would need, anyway you can see here a preview of it.<br>
		On the mean time I have documented on the <a href="/wiki">Wiki</a> the tiny API used 
		to connect to Arianne and a example of how to use the API.<p>
		Also remind you all that we are looking for developers for Arianne. More info 
		<a href="http://sourceforge.net/people/?group_id=1111">here</a>
      ]]>
      </content>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title>Marauroa 0.34 released</title>
    <date>Tue, 18 May 2004 17:15:32 GMT</date>
    <content>
      <![CDATA[server now execute turns on a soft timelimit of 64-100 ms almost with around
         128 players inside, and we have added an out of sync message so that players can 
         request synchronization with server in case of network problems.]]>
      </content>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title>Marauroa speeded up</title>
    <date>Tue, 14 May 2004 21:19:54 GMT</date>
      <images> 
        <image url="images/articles/THM_Marauroa_100Clients.png"/>
      </images>
    <content>
      <![CDATA[
		Today I have improved the speed of Marauroa for around 10 times faster than 
		before by adding a cache of the static part of the perception that is send to each player.<br>
		This improvement allows Marauroa to be able to handle now hundred of players on a dedicated system.<br>
		We only need now to optimize the database subsystem to handle the amount of data.<p>
      ]]>
      </content>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title>pyarianne, wiki and some minor things</title>
    <date>Wed, 12 May 2004 14:59:24 GMT</date>
    <content>
      <![CDATA[
		There are several things moving on arianne right now:<br>
		pyarianne is a python wrapper module for arianne clients, so you can now develop 
		arianne clients using Python and surely pygame :)<p>
		We have setup a wiki to write several docs, if you think you can help us, please 
		do it. <a href="/wiki">Wiki link</a><p>
		Marauroa is moving also in a secure strong way, we are improving the speed of the 
		core game and fixing several things to make it run using as less CPU as possible, 
		so we can increase the player limit actually works correctly with around 64 players.<p>
		On the coming weekend we perhaps do release something. Keep reading.
      ]]>
      </content>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title>Marauroa 0.33 and Gladiators 0.08.4 released</title>
    <date>Sat, 1 May 2004 17:37:12 GMT</date>
    <content>
      <![CDATA[
		A little big step have been taken with Marauroa, this release integrate so many hot fixes 
		and features that the list is long:<ul>
		<li>Static part of the perception, that one that doesn't change depending of the player is
		 precomputed, saving so many CPU cycles</li>
		<li>Added Python RP rules system, allowing to create a simple endless system</li>
		<li>Added mapacman game, our next milestone development</li>
		</ul>
		On the client side, I have been able to remove the nasty memory leak, and now client leaks 
		nothing on the main loop<p>
		The next release of Marauroa, will have a completly explained HOWTO write an online game 
		using the arianne engine
      ]]>
      </content>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title>IRC meeting</title>
    <date>Fri, 30 Apr 2004 20:26:16 GMT</date>
    <content>
      <![CDATA[
		At May, 1 - <a href="http://www.timeanddate.com/worldclock/">18:00 UTC</a> we will have 
		an IRC meeting to talk about Arianne, Marauroa, Gladiators and mapacman state, and future 
		path. The meeting is expected to last one hour. See you tomorrow at 
		<a href="irc://irc.freenode.net#arianne">irc.freenode.net #arianne</a>
      ]]>
      </content>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title>First progresses with mapacman</title>
    <date>Tue, 28 Apr 2004 16:36:47 GMT</date>
    <content>
      <![CDATA[
		On a very experimental framework, I got a pacman to run the laberinth in a more or less 
		''inteligent'' way.<br> Now that I see that is working, I will start to port our designated 
		existing game to use Arianne technology, and the winner is ... Njam. Njam is a a full-featured
		cross-platform pacman-like game written in C++ using SDL library that can be found at 
		<a href="http://njam.sourceforge.net">http://njam.sourceforge.net</a>.
		To have a snack until a playable version arrives I send the output of actual java AI pacman client
<pre>
*************
*+...***...+*
*.**.***.**.*
*.* ......*.*
*.. ***** ..*
***   *.. ***
*   * ..*   *
* *** *.*** *
*+    *....C*
*************
Collision at S --> Goes E
Collision at E --> Goes N
Backtracking detected --> Rotating
</pre>
      ]]>
    </content>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title>Gladiators manual written</title>
    <date>Tue, 27 Apr 2004 18:07:03 GMT</date>
    <content>
      <![CDATA[
		Thanks to Steve I. , we all now have a manual for Gladiators. Please check it 
		and as usual report any kind of problems that you may find.<p>
		Manual is at Documentation: 
		<a href="index.php?arianne_url=games/gladiators/gladiators_manual">manual</a>
      ]]>
      </content>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title>Marauroa 0.32 and Gladiators 0.08.3 released</title>
    <date>Wed, 21 Apr 2004 15:25:46 GMT</date>
    <content>
      <![CDATA[
		This version of marauroa, the arianne's server, fix the bug that happens when an object 
		is added and deleted on the same turn from a slot, adds modification of the network 
		protocol to send our RPObject only when changed, fixed a path related problem with the 
		create account application and finally fixed an issue that rejects the creation of 
		database on the first run.<p>This version of gladiators, our actual client for gladiators 
		game, updates to follow the changes on the server.
      ]]>
      </content>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title>MrPacman to come into Arianne :)</title>
    <date>Tue, 20 Apr 2004 20:56:02 GMT</date>
      <images> 
        <image url="images/articles/real_pacman.jpg"/>
      </images>
    <content>
      <![CDATA[
		As you know we are reaching the begining of another iteration in the Marauroa 
		server ( you know... this is an XP development ). This new iterations add several
 		great things as:<ul>
		<li>a python based rules engine</li>
		<li>a map for storing the enviroment</li>
		<li>the new delta-delta perception system</li>
		<li>persistent accounts world and players</li>
		</ul>This new game will feature a total OS portability and will be based on a 
		existing open source project, so that we show how easy is to modify an existing
 		game to use the Marauroa system to provide game content.
		<p>The progress achieved with Pacman will be applied back into our Gladiators game.
      ]]>
      </content>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title>Marauroa 0.31, Gladiators 0.08.2 and ariannexp 0.08.2 released</title>
    <date>Wed, 14 Apr 2004 12:23:02 GMT</date>
    <content>
      <![CDATA[
	 	 On my way of "release often, release big" I have released a new version of 
	 	 Marauroa that adds the infamous delta-delta algorithm that allows to send only 
	 	 the differences of the objects that have changed, improving so the bandwidth usage.
	 	I also have released a working <i>( I tried them )</i> version of Gladiators 
	 	that is self contained, although you may need to install over 0.07 to get more 
	 	models and a new version of ariannexp that is the text test client that should 
	 	compile and run perfectly on linux too.<p>
	 	Why in the hell there are no progress on gameplay? Nice question, I work alone
	 	( or better: I am working alone ) so I can't develop all by myself. 
	 	<i>root777</i> is doing a nice job at the Java side, but the client is only handled
	 	by me and I can't spend more time ( of what I spend now ) on it. Also our RP game
	 	designer is MIA <i>(miss in accion)</i>, but anyway the progress should come soon.<br>
	 	I do really need help with someone that could take care of a SDL-based graphical
	 	client. I have to keep developing the server side of the game and I am not going 
	 	to be able to keep in sync the client.<p>
	 	Just step on the IRC channel or arianne-devel mailing and I will give you more info.
      ]]>
      </content>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title>Gladiators 0.08 and ariannexp 0.08 released</title>
    <date>Mon, 05 Apr 2004 19:34:52 GMT</date>
    <content>
      <![CDATA[
		I have released a new version of Gladiators and ariannexp that keep in sync with 
		changes on Marauroa. There aren't any gameplay improvements, but I am setting the 
		base for a improved game that should happen soon. BTW now ariannexp is totally compilable and 
 		runable in Linux using autoconf. You need GCC 3.x in order to compile it.<br>
		If you feel nice enough I would be looking for help to write a simple SDL client, 
		I would create all the GFX for you. Just step on the IRC channel or arianne-devel 
		mailing and I will give you more info.
      ]]>
      </content>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title>Marauroa joined Arianne!</title>
    <date>Sat, 27 Mar 2004 16:24:39 GMT</date>
    <content>
      <![CDATA[
		Today Marauroa and Arianne have joined on the task for creating a high quality 
		free and open source multiplayer online game. From this union we can all expect a 
		increment in productivity that will result in more ambitious, and faster achieved
		milestones.<br> Our first task is to implement the new combat system.
      ]]>
      </content>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title>Gladiators 0.07 released</title>
    <date>Fri, 26 Mar 2004 20:25:41 GMT</date>
    <content>
      <![CDATA[
		This is also an update version of Gladiators 0.06 that add support for Marauroa's 
		updated version of the network protocol and that fix the bug related to text output.
		I also have changed per request the location of the text at login time so now it is
		readable. Please test and report problems.
      ]]>
      </content>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title>Gladiators 0.06 released</title>
    <date>Sat, 06 Mar 2004 13:59:12 GMT</date>
    <content>
      <![CDATA[
      	This is an update version of Gladiators 0.05 that add compression to the network 
      	layer so that the bandwidth usage is smaller. Also it is the only version that 
      	will connect to the actual server. Please test and report.]]>
      </content>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title>Gladiators 0.05 released</title>
    <date>Thu, 26 Feb 2004 19:40:26 GMT</date>
      <images> 
        <image url="screens/gladiators/THM_20040226_Gladiators.jpg"/>
      </images>
    <content>
      <![CDATA[
		Again, a new version of Gladiators ( and again for windows only ).<br>This one
		doesn't crash. I have stressed it for 4 hours and I have not been able to crash
		it.<br>So I am really interesting on anyone's story about gladiators  problem.<p>
		Text has been reworked so that it is more "usable" now. You may still have the
		server unreachable problems, I promise to fix it on 0.06. Now error messages are 
		more useful :) and finally fame has been reworked to be more fair and scalable.
      ]]>
      </content>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title>Gladiators 0.04 released</title>
    <date>Sun, 22 Feb 2004 20:28:32 GMT</date>
      <images> 
        <image url="screens/gladiators/THM_20040220_Gladiators.jpg"/>
      </images>
    <content>
      <![CDATA[
		It has been a long time since the last release but finally I have been able to 
		add Chat and the client is stabler than ever. My new goals are to add a shop to
		buy/sell items so that combat can be less random and more interesting.<br>
		I have also added an update version for those of you that already has Gladiators 0.03 ]]>
      </content>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title>New website online</title>
    <date>Sat, 20 Feb 2004 13:31:48 GMT</date>
    <content>
      <![CDATA[
      I have written a new website with in invaluable of Steve. We would really love to listen
      to comments and friendly hands to help improve even more the webpage]]>
      </content>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title>Gladiators 0.03 released</title>
    <date>Wed, 11 Feb 2004 18:12:48 GMT</date>
      <images> 
        <image url="screens/gladiators/THM_20040210_2_Gladiators.jpg"/>
      </images>
    <content>
      <![CDATA[
      	A new week, a new release! :)<br> This version of Gladiators works for sure 
      	( I have tested it several times). Please give it a try and report problems 
      	you have and mainly features you want. <i>Yes, chat, I know. Chat is complex 
      	so I will add in 0.04</i>]]>
      </content>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title>Gladiators 0.02 and ariannexp 0.02: Arianne 0.4.2 released</title>
    <date>Fri, 06 Feb 2004 20:18:48 GMT</date>
      <images> 
        <image url="screens/gladiators/THM_20040206_Gladiators.jpg"/>
      </images>
    <content>
      <![CDATA[
      	This release features better error handling, a music, a nicer mouse pointer 
      	and traces to be able to debug the application remotely. ]]>
      </content>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title>Gladiators 0.01 released</title>
    <date>Sun, 01 Feb 2004 01:53:29 GMT</date>
      <images> 
        <image url="screens/gladiators/THM_20040126_Gladiators.jpg"/>
      </images>
    <content>
      <![CDATA[
		Gladiators is a game where you are the player, and you OWN several characters,
		each characters is a gladiator. As a gladiator your task is to fight and survive
		in the Arena.<br>
		You can also play as a spectator, and join the arena to see the combat and 
		decide the luck of the fighters, as spectator you can decide if the looser die
		or not and the amount of fame that is assigned to each of the fighters.
		Your main goal is to get fame so that you can buy better equipment, and better 
		gladiators.
		This release features better error handling, a music, a nicer mouse pointer and 
		traces to be able to debug the application remotely.
      ]]>
      </content>
  </item>
</website>
